他是我认识的人当中 最不平凡的一个人
He was the most extraordinary man I ever knew.
你跟他很熟吗？
Did you know him well?
我认识他
I knew him.
你要不就是跟他很熟 要不就是不认识他
Well, nil nisi bonum.
但他真的值得…
But did he really deserve...
你们把他葬在这里吗？
a place in here?
艾伦比爵士 你能谈谈劳伦斯上校吗？
Lord Allenby, could you give a few words about Lawrence?
什么？还要再说啊？
What, more words?
沙漠的叛乱事件…
The revolt in the desert...
在中东局势中 扮演着决定性的角色
played a decisive part in the Middle Eastern campaign.
是的，但我想请您 谈谈劳伦斯上校这个人
Yes, sir, but about Colonel Lawrence himself.
不，我跟他不熟，你知道的
No, no. I didn't know him well, you know.
班特尼先生，你可说是最认识劳伦斯
Mr. Bentley, you know as much about Lawrence as anybody.
是的，能认识他…
Yes, it was my privilege to know him.
跟让世人认识他，是我的荣幸
And to make him known to the world.
他是诗人，学者及英勇的战士
He was a poet, a scholar and a mighty warrior.
谢谢
Thank you.
他还是自从巴纳姆跟贝利之后 最无耻的爱现狂
He was also the most shameless exhibitionist since Barnum and Bailey.
您是哪位？
You, sir. Who are you?
我是杰克森班特利
My name is Jackson Bentley.
我听到你刚说的话 并对那提出最严重的异议
I overheard your last remark and take the gravest exception.
-他是个伟大的人 -你认识他吗？
- He was a great man. - Did you know him?
不，我不能说我认识他
No, I can't claim to have known him.
我很荣幸在大马士革跟他握过手
I had the honour to shake his hand in Damascus.
认识他？我从来都不认识他
Knew him? I never knew him.
他曾在开罗为我做些不重要工作
He had some minor function on my staff in Cairo.
麦克乔治哈特利
Michael George Hartley...
这是个又脏又暗的小房间
this is a nasty, dark little room.
没错
That's right.
我们在这里不快乐
We are not happy in it.
我快乐，这要比待在 又脏又暗的的小战壕来得好
I am. It's better than a nasty, dark little trench.
-那么你是个高尚的贵族罗 -没错
- Then you're a big noble fellow. - That's right.
威廉波特拿着我的报纸来了
Here is William Potter with my newspaper.
-拿去吧 -谢谢
- Here you are, Tosh. - Thanks.
你想来根哈特利上校的香烟吗？
Would you care for one of Corporal Hartley's cigarettes?
-有刊登吗？ -当然有
- Is it there? - Of course.
头条新闻
Headlines.
我敢说泰晤士时报 一定没提这条新闻
But I bet it isn't mentioned in the Times.
“贝都因人攻击土耳其要塞”
" Bedouin tribes attack Turkish stronghold."
我敢说连这里总部的人 都不知道这件事
I bet that no one in this headquarters even knows it happened.
或者在乎这件事，我来帮你点烟
Or would care if it did. Allow me to ignite your cigarette.
-劳伦斯先生？ -我就是
- Mr. Lawrence? - Yes.
-您的电报 -谢谢
- Flimsy, sir. - Thank you.
你总有一次会闯祸的 只不过是血肉罢了
You'll do that once too often. It's only flesh and blood.
麦克乔治哈特利 你是个哲学家
Michael George Hartley, you're a philosopher.
你是个怪人！
And you're balmy!
-好痛啊！ -当然会痛罗
- It damn well hurts! - Certainly, it hurts.
那么秘诀是什么？
What's the trick, then?
威廉波特 秘诀就是不要在乎会痛
The trick, William Potter, is not minding that it hurts.
还有如果吉普森上尉要找我
By the way, if Captain Gibbon should enquire for me...
告诉他我去跟将军聊天了
tell him I've gone for a chat with the general.
-他是个怪人 -他还好
- He's balmy. - He's all right.
劳伦斯
Lawrence.
什么事？
Yes?
你应该要…
You're supposed to be...
你通常都是这样乱糟糟地戴着 帽子进来这里的吗？
Do you usually wear your cap in the mess?
我一直都是这样
Always.
你应该在当班 你要去哪里？
You should be on duty. Where are you going?
别跟我说教 佛莱迪，这里是食堂啊
Mustn't talk shop, Freddie, not in the mess.
我要去跟将军谈一谈
I'm going for a powwow with the general.
我不是以长官的身份问你 而是食堂负责人身份在问你
I'm not asking as your superior, but as the secretary of this mess.
我们不要该在当班的人进来
We don't want chaps in here who should be on duty.
请告诉我，你要去哪里？
Where are you going?
我得警告你，劳伦斯！
I must say, Lawrence!
-抱歉 -你是个小丑，劳伦斯
- Sorry. - You're a clown, Lawrence.
不可能人人都是驯兽师
Ah, well, we can't all be lion tamers.
抱歉
Sorry.
真是个谜，戴登
It's an intrigue, Dryden.
我不建议让一个自大愚蠢的中尉
I do not propose to let an overweening, crass lieutenant...
对指挥官的命令不屑一顾 而且还不受到惩罚
thumb his nose at his commander and get away with it.
听起来没有他不是任何大损失
It doesn't sound as though he'd be any great loss.
别那么做，戴登，这是原则问题
Don't try that, Dryden. There's a principle involved.
没错
There is, indeed.
他待在开罗一点用处都没有
He's of no use here in Cairo.
他或许该到阿拉伯去 他清楚时事，长官
He might be in Arabia. He knows his stuff, sir.
你是说他书看得多吧
Knows the books, you mean.
我已经派布莱顿上校去了 他是一位真正的战士
I've already sent out Colonel Brighton, who's a soldier.
如果布莱顿认为我们该出兵 我们会那么做的
If Brighton thinks we should send some arms, we will.
你还需要什么？
Well, what more do you want?
你确定劳伦斯中尉…
That there would be no question of Lieutenant Lawrence...
不会给任何军事上的建议
giving military advice.
天啊，我希望他不会那么做
By God, I should hope not.
只是 （军情总局） 阿拉伯局 希望有自己的人在现场…
It's just that the Arab Bureau would like its own man on the spot to...
做什么？
To what?
对当前形势作一个评估
To make our own appraisal of the situation.
我还要告诉你 这是我跟我手下的意见
I'll tell you, it's my considered opinion and that of my staff...
任何花在贝都因人身上的时间 都是浪费了的时间
that time spent on the Bedouin will be time wasted.
他们是一个偷羊贼的民族
They're a nation of sheep-stealers.
他们的确攻击了麦地纳
They did attack Medina.
土耳其人把他们打的粉身碎骨
And the Turks made mincemeat of them.
我们不知道这件事
We don't know that.
我们知道他们没接受 那没什么，只是段小插曲
We know that they didn't take it. A storm in a teacup, a sideshow.
如果你想听我的意见 我觉得这儿根本是个小插曲
In my opinion, this whole theatre of operations is a sideshow.
真正的战争敌人是德国人 不是土耳其人
The real war's being fought against Germans, not Turks.
战场不在这里而是在西线
Not here, but on the Western front in the trenches.
你的贝都因军队 不管他们是如何称呼自己
Your Bedouin Army, or whatever it calls itself...
他们只不过是一段小插曲中的小配角
would be a sideshow of a sideshow.
伟大的事都是 从很小的开端开始的，长官
Big things have small beginnings, sir.
（军情总局） 阿拉伯局希望阿拉伯发生大事吗？
Does the Arab Bureau want a big thing in Arabia?
在战争结束后 他们会臣服于我们之下吗？
Does the bureau think they'll sit down under us when this war is over?
长官，局里认为 现在的工作是要打胜仗
The bureau thinks the job of the moment, sir, is to win the war.
别告诉我我有什么责任，戴登先生
Don't tell me my duty, Mr. Dryden.
-劳伦斯来了，长官 -请他进来
- Lawrence, sir. - Send him in.
早安
Good morning, sir.
敬礼
Salute.
如果你要抗命，我会逮捕你的
If you're insubordinate, I shall put you under arrest.
-是我的态度 -你的什么？
- It's my manner. - Your what?
长官，我的态度看来像是抗命 但事实上却不然
My manner. It looks insubordinate, but it isn't.
我弄不清楚 你是态度恶劣或是愚蠢
I can't make out whether you're bad-mannered or just half-witted.
-我也有相同的问题，长官 -闭嘴
- I have the same problem, sir. - Shut up.
（军情总局） 阿拉伯局认为你在阿拉伯 应该会派上用场了
The Arab Bureau thinks you would be of use to them in Arabia.
我真想不到什么原因
Why, I can't imagine.
你无法完成你现在的任务
You can't perform your present duties properly.
“我不会拉提琴，但我能让一个 小城市变成一个伟大的国家”
" I cannot fiddle, but I can make a great state from a little city."
-什么？ -那是希米斯特克拉斯的话
- What? - Themistocles, sir.
-他是希腊的哲学家 -我知道你受过高深的教育
- A Greek philosopher. - I know you've been well-educated.
你的档案上是那么说的
It says so in your dossier.
你是我受不了的那种人 劳伦斯
You're the kind of creature I can't stand, Lawrence.
但我想我可能错了
But I suppose I could be wrong.
好了，戴丹 你可以把他带走六星期
All right, Dryden. You can have him for six weeks.
谁知道呢？或许可以把他 变成男子汉，进来！
Who knows? It might even make a man of him. Come in!
什么事？
Yes, what is it?
舰队明天晚上会到赛德港
The convoy will be in Port Said tomorrow night.
-确定了吗？ -是的，长官
- Is that certain? - Yes, sir.
看来似乎没有大炮
There doesn't seem to be any artillery.
但应该要有才对啊！
But there must be artillery!
长官，他要去很远的地方
Sir, this is something of an expedition.
延布（Yenbo）：沙特阿拉伯重要商港
He has to get to Yenbo, find a guide, find the Arabs and then get back.
他得到延布去找向导 找到阿拉伯人然后回来
他在六星期内是办不到的
He can't do that in six weeks.
-那么就两个月吧 -三个月
- Two months, then. - Three.
好吧，三个月，好了 可以让我做点工作了吗？戴丹
All right, three. Now, will you let me do some work, Mr. Dryden?
谢谢您，长官
Thank you, sir.
我想说的是我很高兴 您做了这样的决定
I'd like to say, sir, that I am gratef ul for this.
闭上你的嘴，快滚出去
Shut up and get out.
长官
Sir?
没有该死的大炮 我要怎么打赢一场战争？
How can I fight a bloody war without bloody artillery?
-你是怎么办到？ -你该问我干嘛这么为你费心
- How did you do it? - Might better ask why I bothered to.
-因为我是最合适的人 -我真不知道
- Because I'm the man for the job. - I just wonder about that.
我当然是罗 对了，任务内容是什么？
Of course I am. What is the job, by the way?
费萨尔(Feisal)是阿拉伯哈什米特王族的三王子
Find Prince Feisal.
去找费萨尔王子
好，找到他之后呢？
Good. And when I've found him?
查出他是什么样的人
Find out what kind of a man he is.
查出他有什么企图 不是立即的企图
Find out what his intentions are. Not his immediate intentions.
那是布莱顿上校的事 不是你的事
That is Colonel Brighton's business, not yours.
我是说他在阿拉伯所有的企图
I mean, his intentions in Arabia altogether.
那可新奇了
That's new.
他们现在在哪里？
Where are they now?
在麦地纳方圆三百里内
Anywhere within 300 miles of Medina.
他们是哈希米特贝都因人
They're Hashemite Bedouins.
他们可以在一天内 在沙漠中行走六十里
They can cross 60 miles of desert in a day.
谢谢你，戴丹，这一定会很有趣
Thanks. This is going to be fun.
劳伦斯，沙漠里只有 两种人物可以享乐
Lawrence, only two kinds of creature get fun in the desert:
就是贝都因人跟神，你两者都不是 记住我的话
Bedouins and gods, and you're neither. Take it from me.
对普通人来说 那里像是个炙热的火炉
For ordinary men, it's a burning fiery furnace.
不，戴丹，一定会很好玩的
No, Dryden. It's going to be fun.
大家都认为你的幽默感很有趣
It is recognized that you have a funny sense of fun.
你可以在这里喝点水
Here you may drink.
一杯就好
One cup.
你不喝？
You do not drink?
我不要
No.
你喝我才喝
I'll drink when you do.
我是贝都因人
I am Bedu.
告诉我 你真的是英国军官吗？
Truly, now, you are a British officer?
是的
Yes.
你来自开罗？
From Cairo?
对
Yes.
-你不是从开罗骑骆驼来的？ -不是
- You did not ride from Cairo? - No.
谢天谢地，那可有九百里远啊 我是搭船来的
Thank heaven. It's 900 miles. I came by boat.
之前呢？
And before?
英国来的？
From Britain?
对
Yes.
真的吗？
Truly?
我来自牛津夏尔
From Oxfordshire.
那是沙漠地带吗？
Is that a desert country?
不，那是个富裕的国家 每个人都很富裕
No. A fat country. Fat people.
你不是？
You are not fat?
对
No.
我不一样
I'm different.
好了
Here...
拿去
take it.
我先带你去找费萨尔殿下 你再把它交给我
First I take you to Lord Feisal, then you give it to me.
现在就拿去吧
Take it now.
贝都因食物
Bedu food.
很好吃
Good.
还要吗？
More?
-贝都因人 -哪里？
- Bedu. - Where?
从这里到费萨尔殿下的营地 是哈利斯部落
From here to Lord Feisal's camp is Harith country.
对，我知道
Yes, I know.
-我不是哈利斯人 -对
- I am not Harith. - No.
贝尼沙伦的哈齐尼人
Hazimi, of the Beni Salem.
右腿靠拢，用左腿钩着
Put the right foot in tight. Lock it with your left foot.
当你准备好要走了…
When you are ready to go...
打它的肩膀说“哈，哈，哈”
hit her on the shoulder and say, " Hut-hut-hut."
今天会很辛苦 但明天的行程就轻松了
Today will be difficult, but tomorrow, good riding.
我想我们明天 应该能到马斯杜拉水井
I think we reach Masturah Well tomorrow. Yes.
从马斯杜拉水井到费萨尔殿下 的营地还要一天的路程
And from Masturah Well to Lord Feisal's camp, one day more.
快！
Now!
还好吗？
Good?
还不错
It's all right.
这是哈利斯的水井
This is a Harith well.
哈利斯的人很脏
The Harith are a dirty people.
是土耳其人吗？
Turks?
是贝都因人
Bedu.
他是谁？
Who is he?
他死了
He is dead.
对
Yes.
为什么？
Why?
这是我的水井
This my well.
我从这里取水喝
I have drunk from it.
我欢迎你喝
You are welcome.
他是我的朋友
He was my friend.
-那个吗？ -对，那个
- That? - Yes, that.
-这把手枪是你的吗？ -不，是他的
- This pistol yours? - No, his.
是他的？
His?
是我的
Mine.
那我要把它拿来用
Then I will use it.
你的朋友
Your friend...
贝尼沙伦的哈齐尼人
was a Hazimi of the Beni Salem.
我知道
I know.
我是阿里伊本艾卡利希
I am Ali ibn el Kharish.
我听说过你
I have heard of you.
好了
So...
一个哈齐尼人在这里做什么？
what was a Hazimi doing here?
他要带我去帮助费萨尔王子
He was taking me to help Prince Feisal.
-你是开罗那边派来的人 -对
- You've been sent from Cairo. - Yes.
我是在开罗念书的
I have been in Cairo for my schooling.
我会读跟写
I can both read and write.
费萨尔殿下已经有个英国绅士了
My Lord Feisal already has an Englishman.
你叫什么名字？
What is your name?
我的名字只告诉朋友
My name is for my friends.
我的朋友都不会杀人
None of my friends is a murderer.
你在生气，英国人
You are angry, English.
他什么都不是
He was nothing.
这口水井就是一切
The well is everything.
哈齐尼人 不许喝我们水井里的水
The Hazimi may not drink at our wells.
他知道的
He knew that.
你好
Salaam.
阿里长官
Sherif Ali.
只要阿拉伯的部族战争不休
So long as the Arabs fight tribe against tribe...
他们仍是一个弱小的民族
so long will they be a little people...
一个愚蠢的民族
a silly people.
跟你一样贪婪，野蛮跟残忍
Greedy, barbarous and cruel, as you are.
来吧
Come.
我带你去见费萨尔
I will take you to Feisal.
我不要你陪我一起去，长官
I do not want your company, sherif.
万迪沙法拉离这里 还要一天的路程
Wadi Saf ra is another day from here.
你到不了那里的 到不了那里你就死定了
You will not find it, and you will die.
有了这个，我到得了那里
I will find it with this.
很棒的军队罗盘
Good army compass.
我把它拿走会怎么样？
How if I take it?
那你就是小偷
Then you would be a thief.
你不怕吗？英国人
Have you no fear, English?
怕不怕是我的问题
My fear is my concern.
真的
Truly.
愿真主与你同在，英国人
God be with you, English.
当我自力地走在波斯迪波兰尼
As I walk along the Bois de Boulogne With an independent air
你可以听到女孩子们说
You can hear the girls declare
他一定是百万富翁
He must be a millionaire
我在蒙地卡罗赢光了他们的钱
I'm the man who broke the bank At Monte Carlo
嘿，你！
Hey, you!
-我一直在等你 -你知道我会来？
- I've been waiting for you. - Did you know I was coming?
我知道有人会来 费萨尔告诉我的
I knew someone was coming. Feisal told me.
他怎么会知道？
How did he know?
方圆五十里发生的事 没有一件是费萨尔不知道的
Not much happens within 50 miles of Feisal that he doesn't know.
我相信，没有人陪你来？
I'll give him that. No escort?
我的向导在马斯杜拉水井被杀了
My guide was killed at the Masturah Well.
-土耳其人杀的？ -不，是阿拉伯人
- Turks? - No, an Arab.
残忍的野蛮人
Bloody savages.
-这里是万迪沙法拉，对吧？ -对，他们在那边
- This is Wadi Saf ra, isn't it? - Yes, they're over there.
等一下，你叫什么名字？ 是谁派你来的？
Just a minute. What's your name and who sent you?
我是劳伦斯 我隶属于（军情总局） 阿拉伯局
Lawrence. I've been seconded to the Arab Bureau.
你在为（军情总局） 阿拉伯局做什么？
What are you to do for the Arab Bureau?
不是很清楚 我是来了解这儿的状况
Well, it's rather vague, sir. I'm to appreciate the situation.
那一点都不难，情况非常可怕
Well, that won't be difficult. The situation's bloody awf ul.
他们的士气 我怀疑他们是否有士气
Their morale, if they ever had any, which I doubt...
土耳其人在麦地纳前 用榴弹炮击溃了他们
the Turks knocked out of them in front of Medina, with howitzers.
他们每晚都有好几十个跑掉
They're fading away by dozens every night.
这是我想说的：
What I want to say is this:
不管你在哪里 还有你跟谁在一起
Wherever you are and whoever you are with...
你仍是英国军官，这是命令
you're a British officer. Here's an order.
当我们进入营地时 你得把嘴巴闭上
When we get into that camp, you're to keep your mouth shut.
-你知道我在说什么吗？ -我知道你在说什么
- Do you understand what I'm saying? - I understand what you're saying.
你了解好了以后就回到…
You'll make your appreciation and get back to--
天啊
Oh, my God.
别又来了
Not again.
我告诉过他了 天知道，我告诉过他了
I've told him! God knows I've told him.
我说“往南走 你还在射击范围内”
" Move South, " I've said. "You're still in range."
他们根本不了解 现在武器的威力！
They simply will not understand what modern weapons do!
挺身而战！
Stand and fight. Stand and fight.
向他们还击！
Fire back at them.
-你是谁？ -劳伦斯中尉，长官
- Who are you? - Lieutenant Lawrence, sir.
我隶属于（军情总局） 阿拉伯局
Seconded to the Arab Bureau.
这真的是一团乱 我们真的得往南走
This is a bloody mess, sir. We'll have to move south.
是的，上校，往南走五十里
Yes, colonel, 50 miles south.
你说的对，我错了
You were right and I was wrong.
我们得想想如何处理伤者
We must take some thought for the wounded.
-我们可以到延布帮他们疗伤 -只要他们到得了延布
- We can take care of them at Yenbo. - lf they can get to Yenbo.
他们不可能跟我们一起走
They can hardly come with us.
不，他们得试着到延布去 那个…？
No. They must try to reach Yenbo. Lieutenant...?
劳伦斯
Lawrence.
你明白的，劳伦斯中尉
You understand, Lieutenant Lawrence...
我的人不习惯炸药跟机器
my people are unused to explosives and machines.
先是枪，现在又是这个
First the guns, and now this.
有香烟吗？
Cigarette?
抱歉
I'm sorry.
有烟吗？殿下
Cigarette, Your Excellency?
走开
Umph off.
拜托，殿下 就给我们两个人一根烟？
Please, Your Excellency. Just one for two?
等一下，贾金斯！
Hold it, Jenkins!
贾金斯！
Jenkins!
劳伦斯？
Lawrence?
你没有带随从
You have no servant.
-我不需要随从 -是吗？
- I don't need a servant. - No?
我们什么都会做 生火，煮食物，洗衣服
We can do everything. Light fires, cook food, wash clothes.
-对，什么都会做 -我不怀疑
- Yes, everything. - I don't doubt it.
-那对你来说是件好事 -我负担不起
- It will be very nice for you. - I can't afford it.
那么尽可能地朗读古兰经吧
Recite, then, as much of the Koran as may be easy to you.
天知道你们当中有些病人
God knoweth that there be some among you sick...
其他人在世界到处旅行 寻找真主的恩赐
while others travel through the Earth in quest for the bounties of God.
其他人为他而战
Others do battle in His cause.
所以尽可能地朗读吧
Recite, therefore, as much as may be easy.
服从经文
And observe the prayers.
这将会是最好 最丰硕的报答
This will be best and richest in the recompense.
寻求真主的宽恕
Seek ye the forgiveness of God.
真主是会原谅你 他是那么地仁慈…
Verily, God is forgiving, mercif ul--
你好啊，阿里
Greetings, Ali.
-殿下 -阿里长官
- My lord. - Sherif Ali.
劳伦斯中尉 我想你见过阿里长官了
Lieutenant Lawrence, you have met Sherif Ali, I think.
是的，殿下
Yes, my lord.
这是赛林姆的“光明”
And now, Selim, "The Brightness."
“经由中午的光明”
" By the noonday brightness...
“跟天黑后的夜晚”
and by the night when it darkeneth...
“真主是不会遗弃你的”
thy Lord hath not forsaken thee...
“他也不会不悦”
neither hath He been displeased.
“你的未来当然比过去好”
And surely the future shall be better for thee than the past."
“在最后真主 将会慷慨地赐福于你”
"And in the end shall your Lord be bounteous to thee...
“而你将会满足”
and thou be satisfied."
那么？
So?
是的，上校
Yes, colonel.
-我要你做决定，长官 -你要我撤退回延布
- I want a decision, sir. - You want me to fall back on Yenbo.
你在这里没有大用途
Well, you're not doing much good here, sir.
我很抱歉这么说 但在这里我们不能为你提供补给
I'm sorry to rub it in, sir, but we can't supply you here.
你可以从亚喀巴港来补给我们！
You could supply us through Aqaba!
亚喀巴！
Aqaba!
如果你守得住亚喀巴 我们就能给你补给
If you can get ahold of Aqaba, we can supply you.
-但是你们不能！ -你们可以的
- But you can't! - You could.
你是指海军吗？
You mean, the navy?
土耳其人在亚喀巴 部署了十二寸的大炮
The Turks have 12-inch guns at Aqaba, sir.
你可以想像那是什么意思吗？
Can you imagine what that means?
对，我想像得到
Yes, I can imagine.
别想了，海军还有别的事要做
Put that out of your mind, sir. The navy's got other things to do.
对，保护苏伊士运河
Oh, yes. Protecting the Suez Canal.
前线最重要的地方就是运河
The one essential sector of this front is and must be the canal.
你应该明白的
You can see that, sir, surely.
我知道英国人对运河有兴趣
I see that the canal is an essential British interest.
那对我们来说没什么影响
It is of little consequence to us.
请你不要那么说
I must ask you not to speak like that.
英国跟阿拉伯的目标是一样的
British and Arab interests are one and the same.
有可能
Possibly.
我得说，先生，你很不知感激
Upon my word, sir, you're ungratef ul.
撤退回延布 我们会补充设备给你的
Fall back on Yenbo and we will give you equipment.
给你武器，建议，训练 什么都可以
Give you arms, advice, training, everything.
-枪呢？ -每个人都能有现代的来福枪
- Guns? - A modern rifle for every man.
不，枪，大炮
No. Guns. Artillery.
像是土耳其人在麦地纳用的大炮
Guns like the Turkish guns at Medina.
对，给我们大炮，不用训练我们
Yes, give us guns and keep the training.
你的手下 最需要的是训练而不是大炮
Your men need training far more than guns, sir.
英国人要教 贝都因人如何战斗？
English will teach Bedu to fight?
阿里长官，我们会教他们 对抗一只现代化的机械式军队
We will teach them, Sherif Ali, to fight a modern mechanized army.
是的，中尉？ 延布的事你意见如何？
Yes, lieutenant? What do you think about Yenbo?
我觉得那里离大马士革很远
I think it is far from Damascus.
我们会把你送到大马士革的，别害怕
We'll have you in Damascus, sir. Never fear.
你去过大马士革吗？劳伦斯先生
Have you been in Damascus, Mr. Lawrence?
去过，殿下
Yes, my lord.
那里很漂亮，对吧？
It is beautif ul, is it not?
-非常漂亮 -那就行了，劳伦斯
- Very. - That will do, Lawrence.
梦想不会带你去大马士革 但是纪律可以
Dreaming won't get you to Damascus, but discipline will.
听着，英国是一个小国家 比你的国家还小
Look, Great Britain is a small country, much smaller than yours.
跟某些国家相比人口很少
Small population compared with some.
它很小但很伟大，为什么？
It's small, but it's great. And why?
-因为它有枪 -因为它有纪律
- Because it has guns. - Because it has discipline.
因为它有海军，所以…
Because it has a navy, because of this, the English go where they please...
英国人想去哪里都行
想攻击哪里都没问题 所以他们才会很伟大
and strike where they please. This makes them great.
-对 -劳伦斯先生，那样就行了
- Right. - Mr. Lawrence, that will do!
劳伦斯不是你的军事顾问
Lawrence is not your military adviser.
但我想听听他的意见
But I would like to hear his opinion.
该死！ 你听谁的命令呢？
Damn it! Who do you take your orders from?
在费萨尔的帐篷里 当然是费萨尔殿下
From Lord Feisal, in Feisal's tent.
老笨蛋！为什么问完他后问他 他们一个是主人，一个是随从
Old fool! Why turn from him to him? They are master and man.
殿下，我认为…
My lord, I think...
我认为你的书说的对
I think your book is right.
沙漠是个没有船的海洋
The desert is an ocean in which no oar is dipped.
在这片海洋中贝都因人…
On this ocean, the Bedu go where they please and strike where they please.
想去哪里，想攻击那里都行
贝都因人一直是这样作战的
This is the way the Bedu has always fought.
你因这个战法而名闻世界
You're famed through the world for fighting this way.
你现在正需要这样打法
And this is the way you should fight now.
我不知道
I don't know.
抱歉，先生，你错了
I'm sorry, sir, but you're wrong.
撤退回延布，阿拉伯提升组织 将成为英军的一个单位
Fall back on Yenbo, the Arab Rising becomes one unit in the British army.
-对你来说这有什么好处？ -你是个叛徒
- What is this to you? - You're a traitor.
不，上校
No, colonel.
他是个年轻人，年轻人充满了热忱
He is a young man, and young men are passionate.
他们得说出想说的话
They must say their say.
但聪明人得下决定 我知道你是对的
But wiser people must decide. I know you are right.
那么，我们何时走？越快越好
Very well. When shall we move? The sooner the better.
你今晚会失去五十个手下
You'll lose another 50 men tonight.
你的语气很强硬
You tread heavily...
但你说的话都是真的
but you speak the truth.
我明天会告诉你答案 但是现在…
I will give you my answer tomorrow. And now...
已经很晚了
it is late.
布莱顿上校想把我的人…
Colonel Brighton means to put my men under European officers, does he not?
纳入欧洲军官麾下，对吧？
可以说，是的
In effect, my lord, yes.
我必须这么做
And I must do it...
因为土耳其人有欧洲人的枪
because the Turks have European guns.
但我害怕这么做
But I fear to do it...
我以灵魂发誓，我真的怕
upon my soul I do.
英国人对荒凉之地比较有兴趣
The English have a great hunger for desolate places.
我怕他们想拿下阿拉伯
I fear they hunger for Arabia.
那你得挺身抵抗
Then you must deny it to them.
你是英国人，你不忠于英国吗？
You are an Englishman. Are you not Ioyal to England?
我效忠于英国跟其他事情
To England and to other things.
你同时效忠于英国跟阿拉伯？
To England and Arabia both?
那可能吗？
And is that possible?
我觉得你是 那种喜欢沙漠的英国人
I think you are another of these desert-Ioving English.
两人都是到过中东沙漠的英国旅行家
Doughty, Stanhope...
道迪，史丹霍普
戈登就是镇压太平天国的洋枪队长
Gordon of Khartoum.
喀土穆的戈登
阿拉伯人不喜欢沙漠
No Arab loves the desert.
我们喜欢水跟绿树 在沙漠里什么都没有
We love water and green trees. There is nothing in the desert.
人都是有需求的
And no man needs nothing.
或是你们觉得 我们是你们能玩弄的东西
Or is it that you think we are something you can play with...
因为我们是弱小愚蠢的民族
because we are a little people, a silly people...
贪婪，野蛮又残忍？
greedy, barbarous and cruel?
中尉，你知道 在阿拉伯的卡杜巴市…
Or do you know, lieutenant, in the Arab city of Cordoba...
有两里长的街道设有路灯
were two miles of lighting in the streets...
当时伦敦还只是个小村子
when London was a village.
对，你们很伟大
Yes, you were great.
那是九世纪前的事
Nine centuries ago.
该是你们恢复光荣的时候了，殿下
Time to be great again, my lord.
所以我父亲 决定对土耳其人发动战争
Which is why my father made this war upon the Turks.
劳伦斯先生，是我父亲 不是英国人
My father, Mr. Lawrence, not the English.
但我父亲老了
But my father is old...
而我…
and I...
我渴望着废弃的卡杜巴花园
I long for the vanished gardens of Cordoba.
然而在得到花园前 得先经历苦战
However, before the gardens must come the fighting.
要再度恢复光荣 看起来我们需要英国人
To be great again, it seems that we need the English...
或是…
or...
或是？
Or?
没有人能提供的东西 劳伦斯先生
What no man can provide, Mr. Lawrence.
我们需要奇迹
We need a miracle.
亚喀巴
Aqaba.
从陆地进攻
From the land.
你疯了
You are mad.
经由陆路到亚喀巴 我们得越过尼法德沙漠
To come to Aqaba by land we should have to cross the Nef ud Desert.
没错
That's right.
没人能越过尼法德沙漠
The Nef ud cannot be crossed.
如果你愿意的话，我可以穿越过它
I'll cross it if you will.
你？只靠罗盘是办不到的，英国人
You? It takes more than a compass, Englishman.
尼法德沙漠是真主创造出来 最可怕的地方
The Nef ud is the worst place God created.
我无法为地点做主 我只能为自己作主
I can't answer for the place. Only for myself.
五十个士兵？
Fifty men?
只靠五十个士兵拿下亚喀巴？
Fifty? Against Aqaba?
如果这五十个人 能穿越尼法德沙漠
If 50 men came out of the Nef ud...
会有其他人 加入这五十个人的行列
they would be 50 men other men might join.
听说霍威塔特人在那里
The Howeitat are there, I hear.
霍威塔特人是土匪 他们愿意把自己出卖给任何人
The Howeitat are brigands. They'll sell themselves to anyone.
-但他们是好战士 -没错
- Good fighters, though. - Good--
对，亚喀巴有枪炮
Yes. There are guns at Aqaba.
枪炮都面对大海，阿里长官 而且都无法转向
They face the sea, Sherif Ali, and cannot be turned around.
就内陆这个方面来说 在亚喀巴没有枪
From the landward side, there are no guns at Aqaba.
是有理由的 我们无法从内陆接近亚喀巴
With good reason. It cannot be approached from the landward side.
土耳其人绝对想像不到的
Certainly the Turks don't dream of it.
亚喀巴在那里
Aqaba's over there.
现在只要决定去
It's only a matter of going.
你疯了
You are mad.
你要去哪里？中尉
And where are you going, lieutenant?
还带着我的五十个兄弟
With 50 of my men.
去实现你的奇迹
To work your miracle.
咒骂神明不是旅程的好开始
Blasphemy is a bad beginning for such a journey.
-谁跟你说的？ -阿里
- Who told you? - Ali did.
为什么不是你呢？
Why not you?
你要从延布撤退吗？
You are falling back from Yenbo, sir?
对，我必须撤退
Yes, I must.
但我会让你不必如此
But I will spare these to you.
阿里是否违反誓言告诉我？
Did Ali break confidence to tell me?
阿里长官对你效忠，殿下
Sherif Ali owes you his allegiance, my lord.
但你没告诉布莱顿上校
Yet you did not tell Colonel Brighton.
对
No.
既然你知道…
Since you do know...
我们可以以麦加费萨尔之名展开远征
we can claim to arrive in the name of Feisal of Mecca.
对，劳伦斯中尉，你可以那么说
Yes, Lieutenant Lawrence, you may claim it.
但你要以谁之名展开远征呢？
But in whose name do you ride?
长官，我抓到他们 他们一直在跟踪我们
Sherif, I caught them. They have tracked us.
他们来到这里，我抓到他们
They were here. I caught them.
你们为什么要来这里？小子
Why are you here? Boy!
为了服侍劳伦斯大人，沙利夫
To serve Lord Lawrence, sherif.
真的，劳伦斯 他们真的希望那么做
This is true, Lawrence. They do wish it.
你们一直在跟踪我们
You have been tracking us.
-你奉命要留下来 -不，沙利夫
- You were told to stay. - No, sherif.
我们的骆驼迷路了 我们跟着他走
Our camel strayed. We followed her.
他带我们来这里 当劳伦斯大人的随从
She led us here to be Lord Lawrence's servants.
-这是阿拉的旨意 -你们轻视神明
- It is the will of Allah. - Blasphemy.
别那么做！
Don't do that.
不，劳伦斯，这些人不是随从 他们是无父无母，被放逐的人
No, Lawrence, these are not servants. These are outcasts, parent-less.
我得警告你，他们并不适合
Be warned. They are not suitable.
他们听起来挺适合的 你们负责载运行李
They sound very suitable. You can ride with the baggage.
他们不是随从，他们是朝圣者
These are not servants. These are worshippers.
每星期一先令？
One shilling, every week?
那很公平
That is fair.
-每个人吗？ -不
- Each? - No.
-那太多了 -好吧
- That is too much. - All right.
能被你雇用是他们运气好 阿拉喜欢仁慈的人
They will be lucky for you. Allah favours the compassionate.
铁路在那边
There is the railway.
那边是沙漠
And that is the desert.
从这里到另一边，没有水源 只有我们带来的水
From here until the other side, no water but what we carry.
骆驼根本没水喝
For the camels, no water at all.
如果骆驼死了…
If the camels die...
我们就死定了
we die.
在二十天后，他们会开始死亡
And in 20 days they will start to die.
那么我们别浪费时间了，对吧？
There's no time to waste, then, is there?
我在思考
I was thinking.
你在打瞌睡
You were drifting.
对，以后不会再发生这种事了
Yes. It will not happen again.
小心，你在打瞌睡
Be warned, you were drifting.
以后不会再发生这种事了
It will not happen again.
那些水浪费了
That water is wasted.
从现在开始我们要在晚上出发
From now on, we must travel by night...
热到不能行走时就休息
and rest while it is too hot to travel.
每天只能走几小时
A few hours each day.
我们为什么不现在出发呢？
Why don't we start now?
不，我们现在休息
No. We will rest now.
三小时
Three hours.
好吧
Fine.
我会叫你的
I'll wake you.
我们要在这里休息？
Do we rest here?
没有水，现在别休息
There is no rest now short of water.
那儿的另一边
The other side of that.
那边有多少那儿呢？
And how much of that is there?
我不确定
I'm not sure.
但不管有多少，我们得在 明天太阳升起前越过它
But however much, it must be crossed before tomorrow's sun gets up.
这是个太阳的铁砧
This is the sun's anvil.
完成了吗？
Have we done it?
还没，但我们逃过一劫
No, but we're off the anvil.
谢天谢地
Thank God for that anyway.
对，谢天谢地
Yes, thank Him.
劳伦斯，我想你不知道 你是怎么唆使他的
Lawrence, I do not think you know how you have tempted Him.
我知道
I know.
我们完成了
We've done it.
上天保佑
God willing.
我们何时能到达水井？
When do we reach the wells?
上天保佑，中午
God willing, midday.
-那么我们成功了 -感谢上天吧，劳伦斯
- Then we've done it. - Thank Him, Lawrence. Thank Him.
是嘉西姆的
Gasim's.
他怎么了？
What's happened to him?
天知道
God knows.
你为什么不停下来？
Why don't you stop?
为什么？他中午就会死的
For what? He will be dead by midday.
我们得回去
We must go back.
为什么？为了跟嘉西姆一起死吗？
What for, to die with Gasim?
一小时内太阳会升起
In one hour comes the sun.
以上天为名，听清楚！ 我们不能回头！
In God's name, understand! We cannot go back!
我可以
I can.
把那些男孩带着
Take the boys.
如果你回头，你会害自己没命的
If you go back, you kill yourself, is all.
你已经杀了嘉西姆
Gasim you have killed already.
滚开
Get out of my way.
嘉西姆的时间到了，劳伦斯 那是注定的
Gasim's time is come, Lawrence. It is written.
没有什么事是注定的！
Nothing is written!
那么掉头吧！
Go back, then!
你为什么凭着你咒神又自大地 带着我们来到此地？
What did you bring us here for with your blasphemous conceit?
咒神的英国人！
English blasphemer!
亚喀巴？
Aqaba?
那是亚喀巴吗？
Was it Aqaba?
你到不了亚喀巴的，英国人！
You will not be at Aqaba, English!
掉头吧，咒神狂
Go back, blasphemer...
但你到不了亚喀巴的！
but you will not be at Aqaba.
我会去亚喀巴的
I shall be at Aqaba.
那是注定的…
That is written.
在这里
In here.
英国人！
English!
劳伦斯！杜德！
Lawrence! Daud!
没有什么事是注定的
Nothing is written.
艾尔劳伦斯
Al Lawrence.
法拉吉
Farraj.
洗一洗
Wash.
艾尔劳伦斯
Al Lawrence.
真的，那些不相信命运的人 总是要眼见为凭
Truly, for some men nothing is written unless they write it.
不是艾尔劳伦斯 只是劳伦斯
Not Al Lawrence. Just Lawrence.
-艾尔劳伦斯比较好 -没错
- AI Lawrence is better. - True.
你爸爸也一样吗？ 只是劳伦斯先生
Your father too, just Mr. Lawrence?
我父亲是汤□斯查普曼爵士
My father is Sir Thomas Chapman.
-他是个贵族吗？ -算是吧
- Is that a lord? - A kind of lord.
当他死了之后，你会继承他的地位
Then when he dies, you too will be a lord.
不
No.
你有哥哥
You have an elder brother.
但我不明白，你父亲姓查普曼
But then, I do not understand this. Your father's name is Chapman.
他没娶我母亲
He didn't marry my mother.
我懂了
I see.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
那么我想你可以 自由地选择你的姓氏
It seems to me that you are free to choose your own name, then.
对，我想是的
Yes, I suppose I am.
艾尔劳伦斯是最棒的
Al Lawrence is best.
好吧，那就叫艾尔劳伦斯吧
All right, I'll settle for Al Lawrence.
这是班尼威哈长官的袍子
They are the robes of a sherif of the Beni Wejh.
非常好
Very fine.
-我很荣幸 -我们也很荣幸，您好，长官
- Great honour. - The honour is to us. Salaam, sherif.
-可以这样吗？ -当然
- Is it permitted? - Surely.
没有注定姓氏的人可以 自由地注定你的家族
He for whom nothing is written may write himself a clan.
穿了袍子骑骆驼很方便，试试看
They are good for riding. Try.
你在做什么？英国人
What are you doing, Englishman?
你都看到了
As you see.
你一个人吗？
Are you alone?
差不多吧
Almost.
你跟那些从我井里 取水喝的狗在一起吗？
Are you with those dogs drinking at my well?
那是你的井？
Yours?
我是奥达阿布塔耶
I am Auda Abu Tayi.
我听说过另一个跟你同名的人
I've heard of another man of that name.
另一个人？什么另一个人？
Other? What other?
我听说过的那个奥达 不需要别人帮忙保护他的水井
The Auda I'd heard of wouldn't need to summon help to look after his wells.
他一定是个大英雄
He must be a great hero.
是的
He is.
他不会拒绝提供水 给从尼法德沙漠走出来的人
He wouldn't ref use water to men coming out of Nef ud Desert.
是吗？
Now, would he not?
对，所以他一定是另一个人
No, that must be some other man.
我的助手来了
Here is my help.
孩子，这是什么服装？
Son, what fashion is this?
-这是哈利斯的服装 -哈利斯的什么部族？
- Harith, Father. - What manner of Harith?
这是班尼威哈长官的袍子
A Beni Wejh sherif.
他是哈利斯人吗？
And is he Harith?
不，他是英国人
No, Father, English.
孩子
Son...
他们在偷我们的水
they are stealing our water.
告诉他们我们来了
Tell them we are coming.
告诉他们
Tell them.
-倒光它！ -不要！
- Empty that! - Do not!
我是哈威塔特的奥达
It is Auda of the Howeitat who speaks.
我是哈利斯的阿里
It is Ali of the Harith who answers.
哈利斯
Harith.
阿里
Ali.
你父亲还在偷东西吗？
Does your father still steal?
没有了
No.
奥达把我误认为 他自己的私生子吗？
Does Auda take me for one of his own bastards?
不，根本一点都不像
No. There is no resemblance.
该死，你长得真像你父亲
Alas, you resemble your father.
-奥达是在奉承我 -你很容易就被奉承了
- Auda flatters me. - You are easily flattered.
我跟你父亲很熟
I knew your father well.
你认识你父亲吗？
Did you know your own?
我们有五十个人，你们只有两个 我们开枪射杀你们如何？
We are 50, you are two. How if we shot you down?
那么哈威塔特人会跟你们结下梁子
Why, then you have a blood feud with the Howeitat.
-你希望那样吗？ -在开罗的将军…
- Do you desire it? - Not the generals in Cairo...
跟土耳其国王都不希望这样
nor the sultan himself desire that.
叫你的人退下
Call off your men.
这光荣是属于无价值的
This honours the unworthy.
我才刚开始教他
I've only just begun to teach him.
你今天教了他什么？ 哈威塔特人的待客之道？
And what are you teaching him today? Howeitat hospitality?
别耍嘴皮子，英国人
Be not clever with me, English.
-他是谁？ -他是费萨尔王子的朋友
- Who is he? - A friend of Prince Feisal's.
-你希望我@勤款待你？ -对
- So you desire my hospitality? - Yes.
他是你舌头吗？
Is he your tongue?
我们真的很希望
We do desire it.
如果你要的话，我会答应你的
Then it is given, if you will take it.
我在我的夏日别墅 那是个简陋的地方
I'm at my summer camp, a poor place.
对我来说那是个简陋的地方 有些人觉得那里很棒
Well, to me it seems a poor place. Some men find it marvellous.
明天或许我会准土耳其人买下你 费萨尔的朋友
Tomorrow, maybe I will allow the Turks to buy you, friends of Feisal.
但是…
But...
跟我共进晚餐吧
dine with me.
跟奥达一起用餐，英国人
Dine with Auda, English.
跟哈威塔特人一起用餐 哈利斯人
Dine with the Howeitat, Harith.
我很荣幸能跟你 一起在万迪拉姆用餐！
It is my pleasure that you dine with me in Wadi Rumm!
你要进攻亚喀巴的事…
This thing you work against Aqaba...
你希望得到什么好处呢？
what profit do you hope from it?
我们是为了麦加的费萨尔才这么做的
We work it for Feisal of Mecca.
哈利斯人做事不是为了求好处
The Harith do not work for profit.
如果有人一定要当仆人的话 阿里长官…
Well, if it is in a man to be a servant, Sherif Ali...
也算是个好主人
he could find worse masters than Feisal.
但我不能那么做
But I... I cannot serve.
你允许土耳其人待在亚喀巴
You permit the Turks to stay in Aqaba.
对，那是我的荣幸
Yes, it is my pleasure.
我们这么做不是为了费萨尔
We do not work this thing for Feisal.
是吗？
No?
-那么是为了英国人？ -是为了阿拉伯人
- For the English, then? - For the Arabs.
阿拉伯人？
The Arabs?
哈威塔特，阿吉亚尔，鲁阿拉 班尼夏卡尔，我知道这些部族
The Howeitat, Ageyil, Ruala, Beni Sahkr, these I know.
我听说过哈利斯人
I have even heard of the Harith.
但是阿拉伯人？
But the Arabs?
那是什么部族？
What tribe is that?
他们是奴隶 他们服侍土耳其人
They're a tribe of slaves. They serve the Turks.
他们对我来说什么都不是
Well, they are nothing to me.
我是哈威塔特人
My tribe is the Howeitat.
做事只求好处
Who work only for profit.
我们做事只为了取悦奥达
Who work at Auda's pleasure.
而奥达的乐趣在于服侍土耳其人
And Auda's pleasure is to serve the Turks.
服侍？
Serve?
我会服侍人？
I serve?
拿钱的人是仆人
It is the servant who takes money.
我是奥达阿布塔耶
I am Auda Abu Tayi.
-奥达会服侍人吗？ -不
- Does Auda serve? - No!
- Does Auda Abu Tayi serve? - No!
我身上的二十三处伤痕 都是在战争中受的伤
I carry 23 great wounds, all got in battle.
我在战争中亲手杀了七十五个人
75 men have I killed with my own hands, in battle.
我屠杀燃烧敌人的帐篷 我夺走他们的族人跟牲畜
I scatter, I burn my enemies tents. I take away their flocks and herds.
土耳其人付我金子 但我还是很穷！
The Turks pay me a golden treasure, yet I am poor!
因为我是人民的河流
Because I am a river to my people.
那是服侍吗？
Is that service?
不是
No.
看来奥达老了
And yet now it seems Auda has grown old.
失去了他的战斗力
And lost his taste for fighting.
你敢在我的帐篷里这么说 真是大胆
It is well you say it in my tent, thou old tulip.
这个胆大的人 是土耳其人收买不了的
Yet this is a tulip that the Turks could not buy.
他们为什么要收买他？
Why should they wish to?
好了
Now...
我告诉你他们给我什么 你告诉我这是否是…
I will tell you what they pay me, and you will tell me if this is...
仆人的薪水
a servant's wages.
他们每个月付我…
They pay me, month by month...
一百个金币
100 golden guineas.
是一百五十个，奥达
150, Auda.
-是谁告诉你的？ -我的耳朵挺尖的
- Who told you that? - I have long ears.
你的舌头也很长
And a long tongue between them.
一百跟一百五十有什么差别？ 那只不过是一点钱
100, 150, what matters? It's a trifle.
他们是从一个大箱子 拿出这么一点钱来的
A trifle which they take f rom a great box they have.
在亚喀巴
In Aqaba.
-在亚喀巴 -不然还有哪里？
- In Aqaba? - Where else?
你像女人一样令我烦心
You trouble me like women.
朋友，我们太愚蠢了 奥达不会去的
Friends, we've been foolish. Auda won't come to Aqaba.
-为了钱？ -不
- For money? - No.
-为了费萨尔？ -不
- For Feisal? - No!
也不是为了赶走土耳其人
Nor to drive away the Turks.
他会去…
He will come...
因为那是他的荣幸
because it is his pleasure.
你妈跟子上床
Thy mother mated with a scorpion.
愿老天爷领导你们！
Make God your agent!
亚喀巴！
Aqaba!
愿真主与你同在
God be with you.
对
Yes.
亚喀巴
Aqaba.
明天我们会拿下它
Tomorrow we will go and get it.
-你觉得我们会成功吗？ -会
- Do you think we shall? - Yes.
如果枪炮的事你没说错
If you are right about the guns.
他杀人，他得死
He killed. He dies.
亚喀巴的事到此结束
This is the end of Aqaba.
我们的人杀了奥达的手下
- One of our men murdered Auda's man.
为什么？
- Why?
小偷？世仇？为什么并不重要
Theft? Blood feud? It makes no matter why.
阿里！
Ali!
那是道旧伤口
It is an ancient wound.
我不是来这里看部族血战的
I didn't come here to watch a tribal bloodbath.
这是法律，劳伦斯
It is the law, Lawrence.
法律说这个人得死
The law says the man must die.
如果他死了 哈威塔特人就满意了？
If he dies, will that content the Howeitat?
对
Yes.
阿里长官！
Sherif Ali!
如果奥达大人的手下 不伤害你们…
If none of Lord Auda's men harms any of yours...
-那么哈利斯人会满足吗？ -对
- ...will that content the Harith? - Yes.
那么我要执行法律
Then I will execute the law.
我没有部族
I have no tribe.
没人犯法
And no one is offended.
嘉西姆
Gasim.
那是你做的吗？
Did you do it?
劳伦斯
Well, Lawrence...
英国人在烦恼什么？
What ails the Englishman?
他杀的那个人是 他从尼法德沙漠救回来的
That that he killed was the man he brought out of the Nef ud.
那么那是注定好的
It was written, then.
早知不去救他
Better to have left him.
这是在行刑，劳伦斯 没有什么可耻的
It was execution, Lawrence. No shame in that.
而且这是必要的
Besides, it was necessary.
你让他生，又让他死
You gave life and you took it.
还是由你注定
The writing is still yours.
奥达阿布塔耶！
Auda Abu Tayi!
奇迹发生了
The miracle is accomplished.
征服者的光荣
Garlands for the conqueror.
给王子的贡品，给英雄的花
Tribute for the prince. Flowers for the man.
我什么都不是，阿里
I'm none of those things, Ali.
-那么你是什么？ -我不知道
- What, then? - Don't know.
谢谢
Thanks.
天啊，我爱这个国家
My God, I love this country.
什么！
What!
亚喀巴里没黄金！
No gold in Aqaba!
奥达，我找到了！
Auda, I found it!
那真的是太可惜了
That's a pity.
阿里，把消息传到延布的海边去
Ali, get a message down the coast to Yenbo.
告诉费萨尔找船，什么船都行
Tell Feisal to find boats, any boats...
尽快把阿拉伯军队带到亚喀巴来
and bring the Arab army here to Aqaba, quickly.
你呢？
And you?
我要去告诉…
I'm going to tell the generals...
在开罗的将军们
in Cairo.
对，穿过西奈半岛
Yes, cross Sinai.
来吧！
Come on!
西奈半岛？
Sinai?
对
Yes.
-跟这些人？ -他们跟我在一起没事的
- With these? - They'll be all right with me.
听着，阿里 如果你的贝都因人跑到开罗说：
Look, Ali. If any of your Bedouin arrived in Cairo and said:
“我们拿下亚喀巴了” 将军们会一笑置之
"We've taken Aqaba, " the generals would laugh.
我懂了
I see.
在开罗，你得脱下那些可笑的衣服
In Cairo you will put off these funny clothes.
你要穿上裤子 跟人们诉说我们的古怪跟野蛮
You'll wear trousers and tell stories ofour quaintness and barbarity...
然后他们会相信你
and then they will believe you.
你是个愚昧的人
You're an ignorant man.
纸张
Paper.
纸张！
Paper!
亚喀巴没有黄金
There is no gold in Aqaba.
没有黄金
No gold.
没有大箱子！
No great box!
奥达来到亚喀巴是为了黄金吗？
Did Auda come to Aqaba for gold?
就像你说过的，我是为了荣幸
For my pleasure, as you said.
但黄金是荣耀的东西
But gold is honorable...
而劳伦斯答应会有黄金的
and Lawrence promised gold.
劳伦斯说谎
Lawrence lied.
看好，奥达
See, Auda.
“英国的皇室”
"The Crown of England...
“答应要付”
promises to pay...
“五千个金币”
5000 golden guineas...
“给奥达阿布塔耶”
to Auda Abu Tayi."
“以国王殿下之名”
Signed in His Majesty's absence...
“我在此”
by...
“签名”
me.
十天内…
In 10 days...
我会带着黄金回来
I'll be back with the gold.
我会带枪，黄金跟所有的东西回来
With gold, with guns, with everything.
十天
Ten days.
你要穿过西奈半岛？
You'll cross Sinai?
为什么不行？
Why not?
摩西曾那么做过
Moses did.
你要带着孩子们同行？
And you will take the children?
摩西曾那么做过
Moses did.
摩西是个圣徒
Moses was a prophet...
他受上帝的垂爱！
and beloved of God.
他说过这里有黄金，他骗人
He said there was gold here. He lied.
他不完美
He is not perfect.
天啊，我们能不休息吗？
Lord, can we not rest?
我说过除非他们知道 我拿下亚喀巴，不然不能休息
I told you, no rest till they know that I have Aqaba.
你们两个试过在床上睡吗？
Have you two slept in beds?
法拉吉？
Farraj?
杜德？
Daud?
有床单的？
With sheets?
明天我们会在开罗最好的饭店里 最好的房间盖着最好的床单
Tomorrow the finest sheets in the finest room and hotel in Cairo.
我保证
I promise.
那么就这么说定了，大人
Then it shall be so, lord.
你看！
Look!
是火柱
Pillar of fire.
不，大人，是灰尘
No, lord. Dust.
我的罗盘
My compass.
没关系
No matter.
如果我们往西走 一定可以走到运河那边
If we ride west, we must strike the canal.
往西前进
Due west.
来吧！
Come on!
劳伦斯！
Lawrence!
法拉吉
Farraj!
法拉吉，不要！…
Farraj, don't! Don't!
不要！
Don't!
你为什么要走？
Why do you walk?
为什么？大人
But why, lord?
这可以乘坐两个人，走路没意思
There is room for both. It serves no purpose.
劳伦斯，你看！
Lawrence, look!
(警告)
没关系的，法拉吉
It's all right, Farraj.
没关系的
It's all right.
你是谁？
Who are you?
-杜德！ -我们在这里，大人
- Daud! - We're here, sir.
是你带他来的吗？
You taking him in there?
是的
Yes.
过来！
Here!
你给我过来！
Here. You!
你想去哪里啊？穆斯塔法
And where the hell do you think you're going to, Mustapha?
我们渴了
We are thirsty.
-劳伦斯先生，是吗？ -对
- Mr. Lawrence, is it? - Yes.
-你要去军官酒吧？ -对
- Are you going to the officers' bar? - Yes.
你不能带他进去，先生
You can't take him in there, sir.
你觉得你像什么东西？
What do you think you look like?
不，你得离开
No, no. You must go.
不，来吧，朋友！
No, no. Go, effendi, go!
滚出去！你得滚出去！滚出去！
Get out! You must get out! Get out!
我们要两杯大杯的柠檬汁
We want two large glasses of lemonade.
-这是英国军官的酒吧 -我们并不介意
- This is a bar for British officers. - We are not particular.
-你疯了吗？ -不，很奇怪地我没疯
- Are you off your head? - No. Oddly enough I'm not.
-请你快离开，好吗？ -让那孩子滚出去
- Just clear out of here, will you? - Get that boy out of here.
下士，我们要把这家伙赶出去
Corporal, we'll have this one out anyway.
-把那个混蛋赶出去 -滚开
- Get that wog out of here. - Clear off.
发生了什么事？
What's going on?
-是劳伦斯，长官 -我要加冰的柠檬汁
- It's Lawrence, sir. - Lemonade with ice.
你解释吧
Explain yourself.
我们拿下亚喀巴了
We've taken Aqaba.
-拿下亚喀巴？谁啊？ -我们
- Taken Aqaba? Who has? - We have.
我们的战友拿下亚喀巴 那些混蛋成功了
Our side in this war has. The wogs have.
我们成功了
We have.
他喜欢你的柠檬汁
He likes your lemonade.
你是说土耳其人离开了？
You mean the Turks have gone?
不，他们还在那儿 但是他们已经失势
No, they're still there but they've no boots.
我们把他们全都关了起来 所有的部队都被关了起来
Prisoners, sir. We took them prisoners. The entire garrison.
那不是真的，我们杀了一些人
That's not true. We killed some.
事实上是很多人 我下次会处理的更好
Too many, really. I'll manage it better next time.
不论如何都会死很多人
There's been a lot of killing one way or another.
我发毒誓，那是真的
Cross my heart and hope to die, it's all perfectly true.
-那是不可能的 -那是真的
- It isn't possible. - Yes, it is.
我做到了
I did it.
你最好去跟艾伦比谈谈
You'd better talk to Allenby.
-艾伦比将军？ -现在他是指挥官，墨瑞走了
- General Allenby? - He's in command. Murray's gone.
那么做是对的
That's a step in the right direction.
首先我要一个房间，要有床跟床单
First I want a room. With a bed, with sheets.
-对，当然 -那是给他的
- Yes, of course. - It's for him.
对，你要一张自己的床，对吧？
Right. You want a bed yourself, don't you?
但先去见艾伦比吧
See Allenby first, though.
他会见我吗？
Will he see me?
我想会的
I think so.
那么就去做吧
Do that, then.
-我最好去刮个胡子 -对，没错
- I'd better shave. - Yes, you had.
你最好去换条裤子
You'd better get into some trousers too.
不自律
" Undisciplined.
不守时
Unpunctual.
不整洁
Untidy.
数种语言
Several languages.
音乐
Knowledge of music...
文学的知识
literature.
知识…
Knowledge of...
Knowledge of..."
毫无疑问地你是个有趣的人
You're an interesting man, there's no doubt about it.
-谁要你拿下亚喀巴 -没有人
- Who told you to take Aqaba? - Nobody.
-长官 -长官
- Sir. - Sir.
那么你为什么要那么做？
Then why did you?
-亚喀巴很重要 -为什么它很重要？
- Aqaba's important. - Why is it important?
-那是土耳其人到运河的路线 -不再是了
- It's the Turkish route to the canal. - Not anymore.
-他们现在从比尔沙巴走 -我知道，但我们进入了加萨
- They're coming through Beersheba. - I know, but we've gone to Gaza.
-所以呢？ -拿下亚喀巴对你来说很重要
- So? - So that left Aqaba behind your right.
真的
True.
当你到耶路撒冷时 亚喀巴对你来说就更重要了
And it will be further behind your right when you go for Jerusalem.
我要到耶路撒冷去？
Am I going for Jerusalem?
对
Yes.
非常好
Very well.
亚喀巴对我来说很重要
Aqaba behind my right.
它能威胁艾尔阿瑞许跟加萨
It threatened EI' Arish and Gaza.
还有别的吗？
Anything else?
有
Yes.
亚喀巴跟麦地纳相连
Aqaba's linked with Medina.
你觉得我们现在 要把他们赶出麦地纳吗？
Do you think we should shift them out of Medina now?
不，我想你们 应该把他们留在那里
No. I think you should leave them there.
你在没接到 命令的情况下擅自行动
You acted without orders, you know.
军官不是随时 都该主动进取吗？
Shouldn't officers use their initiative at all times?
事实上不然，那太危险了
Not really. It's awfully dangerous.
对，我知道
Yes, I know.
你已经知道了？
Already?
对
Yes.
我要把你升上少校
I'm promoting you major.
我不觉得那是个好主意
I don't think that's a very good idea.
我没问你意见，我要你回去…
I didn't ask you. I want you to go back...
继续执行你的成果
and carry on the good work.
不，谢谢您，长官
No. Thank you, sir.
-为什么不？ -我，那个…
- Why not? - Well, l, it's...
我想想看…
Let me see now...
我杀了两个人，我是说阿拉伯人
I killed two people. I mean, two Arabs.
其中一个是个孩子
One was a boy.
那是…
That was...
昨天的事
yesterday.
我把他领进流沙里
I led him into a quicksand.
另一个是个男人
The other was a man.
那是在…
That was...
我们拿下亚喀巴之前的事
before Aqaba, anyway.
我得用我的枪来处决他
I had to execute him with my pistol.
我不喜欢这样的事
There was something about it I didn't like.
-当然 -不，还有别的事
- Well, naturally. - No. Something else.
没关系，把它当成是个警告吧
That's all right. Let it be a warning.
不，还有别的事
No. Something else.
什么事？
What, then?
我喜欢那样
I enjoyed it.
胡说八道，你疯了，你太累了
Rubbish. Rubbish and nerves. You're tired.
你打扮成那样是什么意思？ 你现在是业余演员？
What do you mean coming dressed like that? Amateur theatricals?
对，没错
Yes. Entirely.
让我看看那个像帽子的东西
Let me see that hat thing or whatever it is.
他们的装备很棒
Fascinating gear they wear.
我穿起来怎么样？哈利
How would I look in this, Harry?
-很可笑，长官 -拿去，你留着吧
- Damn ridiculous, sir. - Here, you keep it.
我想说的是我并不适合
What I'm trying to say is I don't think I'm fit for it.
真的吗？你觉得呢？戴丹
Really? What do you think, Dryden?
在他那么做之前，长官 我会说那是不可能的
Before he did it, sir, I'd have said it couldn't be done.
-布莱顿？ -我知道他的想法
- Brighton? - I know what he thinks.
我想你该进行授勋典礼
I think you should recommend a decoration, sir.
我觉得他的动机不重要
I don't think it matters what his motives were.
他指挥军队很出色
It was a brilliant bit of soldiering.
-柏金斯先生！ -长官！
- Mr. Perkins! - Sir!
我们去喝一杯吧，男士们
Let's have a drink, gentlemen.
-你听说了吗？柏金斯先生 -我听说了
- You've heard about this, Mr. Perkins? - Yes, sir.
-你觉得如何？ -真的是太棒，长官，做得好
- What do you think about it? - Bloody marvellous, sir. Well done.
-谢谢你，柏金斯先生 -长官
- Thank you, Mr. Perkins. - Sir!
那么来吧
Come on, then.
你是个聪明人
You're a clever man, sir.
不，我懂得把握机会
No, but I know a good thing when I see one.
那很公平，对吧？
That's fair, surely?
若我得在耶路撒冷那边有突破 我得集中力量，不是消散力量
If I need a breakthrough to Jerusalem, I must concentrate, not dissipate.
-太棒了 -你懂吗？
- Bravo. - You know better?
我跟克劳西威兹般作战 然后你像萨克森一样作战
I fight like Clausewitz, then you fight like Saxe.
我们可以做得很好，对吧？
We should do very well indeed, shouldn't we?
男士们，轻松点
Easy, gentlemen, please.
-麻烦你端杯酒来 -没问题
- Give us a drink. - Of course, sir.
我是受劳伦斯少校之邀前来的
I'm here at the invitation of Major Lawrence.
崔西
Tracy.
我们要到外面去吗？
Shall we go outside?
你牵制住土耳其的沙漠军队了？
So you hold bound the Turkish desert army?
对
Yes.
用一千个阿拉伯人？
With 1000 Arabs?
一千个阿拉伯人 代表一千把刀子
1000 Arabs means 1000 knives.
不论日夜他们随时待命
Delivered anywhere, day or night.
代表着一千只骆驼
It means 1000 camels.
那代表一千包的炸药 跟一千把的来福枪
That means 1000 packs of high explosives and 1000 crack rifles.
当土耳其人还在团团转时 我们可以越过阿拉伯
We can cross Arabia while Johnny Turk is still turning round.
我要粉碎他们的铁路
I'll smash his railways.
当他们忙着修护铁路时 我会在别地发动破坏行动
While he mends, I'll smash them somewhere else.
在十三个星期内 我可以让阿拉伯陷于混乱
In 13 weeks I can have Arabia in chaos.
那么你要回去罗？
You are going back, then?
对
Yes.
我当然要回去
Of course I'm going back.
如果我们想得到 那么土耳其人也想得到
Well, if we can see it, so can the Turk.
如果他们发现得用四个军队 来防守一小群的土匪…
If he finds he's using four divisions to fend off a handf ul of bandits...
他们会撤退的
he'll withdraw.
他们不敢撤退的 阿拉伯是他们帝国的一部份
He daren't withdraw. Arabia's part of his empire.
如果他们现在离开 他们永远都无法回来了
If he gets out now, he'll never get back again.
-不知道谁能拥有此地 -没有人可以
- I wonder who will. - No one will.
阿拉伯现在是阿拉伯人的
Arabia's for the Arabs now.
反正我是那么告诉他们的
That's what I've told them anyway.
他们是那么想的
That's what they think.
-那就是他们战斗的原因 -当然
- That's why they're fighting. - Oh, surely.
他们只有一个怀疑
They've only one suspicion.
我们让他们赶走土耳其人 然后自己占据了阿拉伯
That we'll let them drive the Turks out and then move in ourselves.
我告诉他们那是不对的 我们对阿拉伯没兴趣
I've told them that that's false, that we have no ambitions in Arabia.
是吗？
Have we?
谢天谢地，我不是政客
I'm not a politician, thank God.
我们对阿拉伯有兴趣吗？戴丹
Have we any ambition in Arabia, Dryden?
这是个很难的问题
Difficult question, sir.
我想知道能否以你之名告诉他们
I want to know, sir, if I can tell them in your name...
我们对阿拉伯没兴趣
that we've no ambitions in Arabia.
当然可以
Certainly.
两千件兵器还不够 我需要五千件
2000 small arms, not enough. I need five.
好
Right.
还有钱，我要金币 他们不喜欢纸钞
Money. It'll have to be sovereigns. They don't like paper.
-刘易斯机枪的教官 -好
- Instructors for the Lewis guns. - Right.
更多的钱
More money.
-更多是多少？ -现在要两万五，日后要更多
- How much more? - 25, 000 now. A lot more later.
-戴丹？ -没问题，长官
- Dryden? - It can be done, sir.
几部武装车辆
A couple of armoured cars.
好
Right.
大炮
Field artillery.
好
Right.
我会尽力提供你需要的东西
I'll give you every blessed thing I can...
因为我知道你会用到它们，恭喜
because I know you'll use it. Congratulations.
谢谢你们的招待，绅士们
Thank you for your hospitality, gentlemen.
恭喜！
Congratulations!
你真的要给他们大炮吗？长官
Are you really going to give them artillery, sir?
我很怀疑啊
I was wondering that, sir.
要把它们拿回来可能很难
Might be difficult to get it back.
给他们大炮，等于让他们独立
Give them artillery and you've made them independent.
那就不能给他们大炮，对吧？
Then I can't give it to them, can I?
-那是你的决定 -不是
- For you to say. - No, it's not.
我得遵守命令，谢天谢地
I've got orders to obey, thank God.
跟那个可怜的家伙不同
Not like that poor devil.
他像是在骑着旋风
He's riding the whirlwind.
希望我们不是
Let's hope we're not.
(休息时间)
对不起，朋友 这些袋子是什么人的？
Excuse me, friend. Who do these bags belong to?
是费萨尔王子的
To Prince Feisal.
-你不是费萨尔王子吧？ -我不是
- You're not Prince Feisal? - No.
你认识他吗？
You know him though?
他是我的主人，我是他的仆人
He is my master. I am his servant.
你识字吗？
Can you read?
(J.E.班特利先生)
我是芝加哥快报的记者 但我文章在美国多家报社刊登
Chicago Courier is my paper, but my work is syndicated in America.
我从你的来信中知道了 班特利先生
I understood so from your letter, Mr. Bentley.
好了
Now...
-我在哪里能找到劳伦斯少校？ -那是你来此地的目的吗？
- Where can I find Major Lawrence? - Is that what you have come for?
我不是只为了这件事而来
Not altogether, sir, no.
班特利先生 劳伦斯少校在我的军队里
Well, Mr. Bentley, you will find Major Lawrence with my army.
那就是我的意思，先生 我在哪里能找到你的军队？
That's what I meant, sir. Where can I find your army?
我不知道
I don't know.
-上星期他们在艾尔盖拉附近 -盖拉？
- Last week they were near El Ghira. - Ghira?
对，恐怕你得走上一段路 你会骑骆驼吗？
Yes, I fear you have a long journey. Can you ride a camel?
-我从来都没试过 -那你骑骡子吧
- I've never tried. - Take a mule.
避开米拉哈，那里有土耳其人
A void Mellaha, the Turks are there.
他们现在在米拉哈？ 他们的动作真快
In Mellaha now? They move fast.
没错
They do.
但没我们快，你会看到的
But not so fast as we do, you will find.
我自己…
Myself...
要到开罗去
I am going to Cairo.
-你是知道的 -对
- As you know. - Yes.
那里有别的工作等着我去做
There's work for me there of a different kind.
对
Yes.
我知道你一直都没拿到大炮
I know you've been given no artillery.
-没错 -你陷入困境了？
- That is so. - You're handicapped?
这让我们被局限在小事上
It restricts us to small things.
正是他们的计划
It's intended to.
你认识艾伦比将军吗？
Do you know General Allenby?
小心艾伦比 他是个狡猾的家伙
Watch out for Allenby. He's a slim customer.
-对不起 -他是个聪明人
- Excuse me? - A clever man.
狡猾的家伙，说的好
Slim customer. It's very good.
我当然会小心他 你真的是太好心了
I'll certainly watch out for him. You're being very sympathetic.
殿下，美国人也曾是殖民
Your Highness, we Americans were once a colonial people.
我们当然会同情
We naturally feel sympathetic to any people...
那些为争取自由而努力的人
who struggle for their freedom.
真的是太好了
Very gratifying.
还有我的目的跟你一样 你希望世人知道你的故事
Also, my interests are the same as yours. You want your story told.
我很需要一个这样的故事
I badly want a story to tell.
你在胡扯了，对吧？
Ah, now you are talking turkey, are you not?
我会派响导给你 并帮你写一封信的
I will give you a guide and a letter.
在我离开这里之前…
And before I leave here...
我得立刻离开
which must be presently...
我会写下一些事实跟数字给你
I will have some facts and figures put on paper for you.
你知道我们在破坏土耳其人的铁路
You know that we are destroying the Turkish railways.
是的，殿下
I do, sir.
劳伦斯少校负责这次的行动，对吧？
Major Lawrence is in charge of all this, is he?
我的军队是由沙漠部族所组成的
My army is made up of tribes.
部族是由族长所领导
The tribes are led by the tribal leaders.
你的人民很尊重劳伦斯少校吗？
Your people do think very highly of Major Lawrence?
没错，你说的对
Oh, yes. And the rightly.
班特利先生，在这个国家…
In this country, Mr. Bentley...
能够为战争带来胜利的人…
the man who gives victory in battle is prized...
能得到最高的尊敬
beyond every other man.
我现在就可以告诉你一个人…
One figure I can give you f rom my head...
因为我从没忘记过
because it never leaves my head.
自从四个月前开始这项行动后 我们有…
Since starting this campaign four months ago, we have lost...
三十七人受伤…
37 wounded...
一百五十六人死亡
156 dead.
请注意死伤人数的比例不平衡
You remark the disproportion between our dead and wounded.
对
Yeah.
死者比伤者多了四倍
Four times as many.
那是因为 我们会杀了受伤太重的人
That's because those too badly wounded to bring away, we ourselves kill.
我们不会让伤者 落入土耳其人手中
We leave no wounded for the Turks.
-你是说…？ -我们不会让伤者落入敌人手中
- You mean...? - We leave no wounded for the Turks.
在他们的眼中 我们不是士兵而是叛徒
In their eyes, we are not soldiers but rebels.
叛徒不管是受伤还是健全 都不受日内瓦公约保护…
Rebels, wounded or whole, are not protected by the Geneva Code...
而且被敌人残忍地虐待着
and are treated harshly.
有多残忍？
How harshly?
那种情况是你想像不到的
More harshly than I hope you can imagine.
我懂了
I see.
我们的囚犯受到妥善照顾 直到我们…
Our own prisoners are taken care of until the British...
根据公约把他们放给英国人
can relieve us of them, according to the Code.
-我希望你能记住这一点 -是的，先生
- I should like you to notice that. - Yes, sir.
那是劳伦斯少校的影响吗？
Is that the influence of Major Lawrence?
你为什么会那么想？
Why should you suppose?
只是我在开罗听说…
It's just that I heard in Cairo that...
劳伦斯少校讨厌杀人
Major Lawrence has a horror of bloodshed.
事实的确如此
That is exactly so.
对劳伦斯少校而言 仁慈是他所爱的
With Major Lawrence, mercy is a passion.
对我来说那只是一种好礼貌
With me, it is merely good manners.
你可以判断 哪一项动机比较信得过
You may judge which motive is the more reliable.
-好了，或许… -当然
- And now, perhaps... - Oh, sure, sure.
谢谢您，先生
Thank you, sir.
你能把信写得…？
Can you manage the letter--?
我会实践我说过的话…
I'll do everything I have said...
只要你诚实地告诉我 你为何对…
if you will tell me truly the nature of your interest...
我的人民跟劳伦斯少校的事有兴趣
in my people and Major Lawrence.
很简单，先生 我在寻找一个英雄
It's very simple, sir. I'm looking for a hero.
没错，你看起来 不像是个浪漫的人
Indeed. You do not seem a romantic man.
对
Oh, no.
但我老家那些有影响力的人相信…
But influential men back home believe it's time for America...
美国该挺身而出对抗德国
to lend her weight to the struggle against Germany.
跟土耳其
And Turkey.
我来采访新闻 告诉我的国人这场战争…
I've been sent to find material to show our people that this war is...
-很好玩？ -不是那样的，先生
- Enjoyable? - Hardly that, sir.
是用更冒险的角度来报导它
But to show it in its more adventurous aspects.
你在寻找一个能让 你的国家参战的人
You look for a figure who will draw your country towards war.
好吧，对
All right. Yes.
劳伦斯是你要的人
Lawrence is your man.
停火！
Stop!
Stop it!
停火！
快点，大伙们！
Come on, men!
劳伦斯！
Lawrence!
天啊！
Good God! God!
吉米尼！我从没看过 有人这样被剑杀死
Jiminy! Never seen a man killed with a sword before.
你为什么不照张相呢？
Why don't you take a picture?
我希望我照了
Wish I had.
你好吗？劳伦斯
How is it with thee, Lawrence?
我在里面吗？
Am I in this?
你有帮他拍照吗？
Did you take his picture?
拍了
Yeah.
很快地你的九条命都会没了
You are using up your nine lives very quickly.
你的同伴挺不错的
Charming company you keep.
奥达？
Auda?
他有点老古板，他觉得 这些东西会吸走他的灵魂
He's a bit old-fashioned. He thinks these things will steal his virtue.
他觉得你是小偷
He thinks you're a kind of thief.
可以替你拍张照吗？
It's all right to take your picture?
-好吧 -好
- All right. - Okay.
走吧
Just walk.
劳伦斯少校！
Major Lawrence!
对，这才是我的宝贝
Yes, sir, that's my baby.
这种洗劫的行为得停止！
This looting has got to stop!
这是习俗
It is customary.
这是偷窃，小偷才会偷东西
It's theft. And theft makes thieves.
我不会那么跟奥达说
I would not say that to Auda.
-那是他们的薪水，上校 -薪水
- It is their payment, colonel. - Payment.
真的，英国士兵没有薪水吗？
Truly. Are not British soldiers paid?
-他们拿了薪水就不想回家 -他们无法自由回家
- They don't go home when being paid. - They are not free to.
你再不会看到他们了
Well, there's another lot you've seen the last of.
他们会回来的
They'll come back.
他说他们会回来，会吗？
He says they'll come back. Will they?
今年不会，劳伦斯
Not this year, Lawrence.
听着，劳伦斯，你觉得你们 会剩下多少人？两百人吗？
Look, Lawrence, how many men do you think you'll have left? 200?
-会更少 -那么是多少？
- Less. - Well, then?
我说过他们会回来的
I said, they'll come back.
你伤的很重吗？
You badly hurt?
我根本没受伤
Not hurt at all.
你不知道吗？ 他们只有用金子弹才杀得了我
Didn't you know? They can only kill me with a golden bullet.
(小市民，我们的国会)
这是给孩子的书 我得督促自己再学一次
It is for children. I have set myself to learn again.
-你从这件事里学到什么？ -政治
- What are you learning from this? - Politics.
你会在本国行民主政治吗？ 你会成立国会吗？
You'll be a democracy in this country? You gonna have a parliament?
当我成立了国家 我再回答你这些问题
I will tell you that when I have a country.
我回答得好吗？
Did I answer well?
你回答了，但什么都没说 那就是政治
You answered without saying anything. That's politics.
你学的很快
You learn quickly.
我有一个好老师
I have a good teacher.
对
Yeah.
-你伤得如何？ -我很好
- How's your hurt? - Fine.
在我回到战场前 而且我非常乐意那么做
Before I return to the fleshpots, which I shall be very glad to do...
我能直接地问你两个问题吗？
may I put two questions to you, straight?
我想听你直接地问一个问题
I'd be interested to hear you put a question straight.
一
One.
你觉得这些人希望从 这场战争里得到什么？
What, in your opinion, do these people hope to gain from this war?
他们希望获得他们的自由
They hope to gain their freedom.
自由
Freedom.
“他们希望获得他们的自由”
"They hope to gain their freedom."
-他们受骗了 -他们会得到自由的
- There's one born every minute. - They're going to get it.
我会让他们得到自由的
I'm going to give it to them.
-第二个问题呢？ -我要问的是…
The second question?
Well, I was going to ask...
沙漠是什么地方吸引你呢？
what is it that attracts you personally to the desert?
它很干净
It's clean.
好了
Well, now...
那是个很棒的答案
that's a very illuminating answer.
我可以…
May I...
拍一张告别照片吗？
take one farewell picture?
我给麦斯巴德两个灯才换到它
I gave Math Budad two lamps for it.
一个钟换两个灯
One clock for two lamps.
一项很公平的交易
A fair bargain.
公平？我是在抢劫他
Fair? I robbed him.
垃圾
Trash.
我得找到一些荣耀的东西
I must find something honorable.
荣耀的东西？
Honorable?
今年快过完了，布莱顿
The year is running out, Brighton.
我得找到一些荣耀的东西
I must find something honorable.
你现在可以炸了我的火车
Now you may blow up my train.
你要做什么？
And what will you do now?
我现在要回家 他们把我的玩具载走
Now I go home. They will carry my toys.
他们也会载我的玩具 你懂吗？
They will carry my toys too, see?
劳伦斯少校 今年冬天会发动攻势
Major Lawrence will campaign this winter.
但你得到你想要的东西 所以要回家去，对吧？
But you got what you wanted, so you're going home, is that it?
当然，当劳伦斯得到他 想要的东西，他会回家去的
Of course. When Lawrence has got what he wants, he will go home.
当你得到你想要的东西时 你也会回家去的
When you've got what you want, you will go home.
不，我不会的，奥达
No, I shan't, Auda.
那么你是个笨蛋
Then you are a fool.
或许吧，我不是个逃兵
Maybe. But I am not a deserter.
谢天谢地，布莱顿
Give thanks to God, Brighton...
当他把你变成一个呆瓜时 他也让你一脸的呆相
that when He made you a fool, He gave you a fool's face.
你是个无礼的混蛋
You are an impudent rascal.
我得走了，劳伦斯 不然我也要成为笨蛋了
I must go, Lawrence, before I soil myself with a fool's blood.
我像是在对牛弹琴
Like talking to a brick wall.
你现在要做什么？ 你能做什么？
So what will you do now? What can you do?
我要往北走
I'll go north.
那就是艾伦比想要的
That's what Allenby wants.
艾伦比要阿拉伯军队撤到迪拉之后
Allenby wanted the Arab army behind Deraa.
那么我会把他们领到那儿
Then that's where I'll take it.
叫艾伦比快一点，不然在他 到耶路撒冷前我们就到迪拉了
Tell Allenby to hurry up, or we'll be in Deraa before he's in Jerusalem.
对吧？
Won't we?
火车，法拉吉
Train, Farraj.
对，劳伦斯
Yeah, Lawrence.
躲起来，我的朋友
Hide yourself, my friend.
引爆器
Detonator.
好了，再拿一个来
All right, fetch another.
-对不起，劳伦斯，我放… -时间还很多，再拿一个来
- Pardon, Lawrence. I put-- - Plenty of time. Fetch another.
法拉吉？
Farraj?
-发生什么事了？ -引爆器！…
- What happened? - Detonator. A detonator!
他无法骑乘了
He cannot ride.
如果他们活抓他 你知道他们会如何折磨他的
If they take him alive, you know what they'll do to him.
杜德会生你气的
Daud will be angry with you.
帮我向他致意
Salute him for me.
你现在要做什么？
What will you do now?
往北走
Go north.
只带二十个人？
With twenty?
你建议我该怎么做呢？
What would you recommend me to do?
你会如何建议呢？
What would you recommend?
他手下的人不到十分之一
He hasn't 1l10 so many men, sir.
事实上他在骗人
He's lied, in fact.
对也不对，他没说 他有做出他根本没做的事
Yes and no. He doesn't claim to have done anything he hasn't done.
那么就有一队阿拉伯北军罗
Then there is an Arab north army.
-不，长官，他在这一点说谎 -你知道为什么吗？
- No, sir, he has lied about that. - Any idea why?
-我想那是他的军队 -那是费萨尔王子的军队
- It's his army, I suppose. - It's Prince Feisal's army.
你觉得他会被同化吗？哈利
Do you think he's gone native, Harry?
不会的
No.
我想如果可以的话，他会的
He would if he could, I think.
-就我对国家的观念不会的 -这不重要，我只是好奇
- Not my line of country. - It doesn't matter. Just curious.
重要的是我相信它
What matters is I believed it.
土耳其人相信它
The Turks believe it.
他们提供两万镑在悬赏他
They are offering 20, 000 pounds for him.
天啊
Good heavens.
-看来他活不久了 -他是个勇敢的人…
- Shouldn't say he had long to live. - Well, he's a brave man--
没错，如果他还敢带 五十个人北行，他的确很有种
Surely. If he's still going north with 50 men, he doesn't lack guts.
不知道他们 会不会出这么多钱来悬赏我
I wonder if they'd offer that much for me.
明年呢？他们还会回来吗？
What about next year? Will they still come back?
我并不讶异
I wouldn't be surprised.
-他们觉得他是圣徒？ -是他们或是他？
- They think he's a kind of prophet. - They do or he does?
-我可以说句话吗？ -当然可以
- Now may I speak? - Yes.
再失败一次 你会发现自己孤独一人
One more failure and you will find yourself alone.
-不包括我 -不包括其他人
- I do not include myself. - I do not include the others.
他们爱你
So say they love you.
更应该对他们要求低些
The more reason to be thrifty with them.
给他们做的好的任务 但你没那么做
Give them something to do that can be done. But you, no.
他们得移开高山 在水面上行走
They must move mountains, walk on water.
没错
That's right. That's right.
你凭什么知道人能做什么事？
Who are you to know what can be done?
若我们完成你觉得可以 做到的事，我们早在延布了
If we'd done what you thought could be done, we'd be in Yenbo now.
我要他们做到的事都能做得到 你不明白，他们也明白
Whatever I ask them to do can be done. They know that if you don't.
你认为我只是一个普通人？
Do you think I'm just anybody?
是吗？
Do you?
我的朋友谁要跟我走在水面上？
My friends, who will walk on water with me?
-谁要跟我进入迪拉？ -迪拉戒备森严
- Who will come with me into Deraa? - Deraa is garrisoned.
你要以二十人攻打两千人？
Will you take 20 against 2000?
-如果有必要，我会自己去 -为什么？
- I'll go by myself if I have to. - Why?
我告诉英国将军…
I told the English generals...
当他们到耶路撒冷时 阿拉伯暴动会在迪拉
the Arab revolt would be in Deraa when they'd be in Jerusalem.
或许你是为了英国的将军们…
Or perhaps you are here...
来到这里
for the English generals.
谁说的？
Who says this?
传言是如此
Rumour.
那不算是争论
That is not an argument.
争论
Oh, argument.
今天下午当阿拉伯人还在争论…
This afternoon I will take the Arab revolt into Deraa...
我要带阿拉伯暴动进入迪拉
while the Arabs argue.
你能在阿拉伯的村落 假扮成阿拉伯人而不被认出吗？
Can you pass for an Arab in an Arab town?
可以，如果你们愿意 借我一些脏衣服
Yes. If one of you would lend me some dirty clothes.
那太疯狂了
It's madness.
你在找什么？
What are you looking for?
宣布我的到来的方法
Some way to announce myself.
对他有点耐心，天啊
Be patient with him, God.
-你不知道他们怎么看你吗？ -冷静，阿里，没人看得到我
- Do you not see how they look at you? - Peace, Ali, I am invisible.
站住！
Halt!
继续走
Walk on.
-站住！ -继续走
- Halt! - Walk on.
你跟你
You and you.
你
You.
你的眼珠是蓝色的
You have blue eyes.
-我说你的眼珠是蓝色的 -对，朋友
- I say you have blue eyes. - Yes, effendi.
-你是瑟卡新人吗？ -对，朋友
- Are you Circassian? - Yes, effendi.
你几岁？
How old are you?
我二十七岁，朋友
Twenty-seven, effendi.
我想
I think.
你看起来比实际年龄老 你一定经历过很多事
You look older. You have had a lot of experience.
那是个长得很有趣的脸
It's an interesting face.
我被牛包围着
I am surrounded by cattle.
他根本连有趣的脸 是什么都不知道
He wouldn't know an interesting face f rom a sow's belly.
我到迪拉来三年半了
I have been is Deraa now for three and a half years.
就是他们把我派到月球背面布岗 我也不会觉得…
If they posted me to the dark side of the moon, I could not be more...
孤单
isolated.
你不知道我在说什么
You haven't the least idea what I'm talking about.
对，朋友
No, effendi.
是吗？
Have you?
对
No.
那真的是…
That would be too...
太幸运了
lucky.
你打哪弄来这个？
Where did you get that?
-这是旧伤了，朋友 -不，这是新的
- It's old, effendi. - No, this is recent.
-你是个逃兵 -不是的，朋友
- You are a deserter. - No, effendi.
是，你是个逃兵
Yes, you are a deserter.
但是从哪个军队逃出来的呢？
But from which army?
那不重要
Not that it matters at all.
人不可能老是穿制服
A man cannot be always in uniform.
你的皮夫很漂亮
Your skin is very fair.
打他
Beat him.
给我！
To me!
睡吧
Sleep.
吃
Eat.
你有个跟其他男人一样的身体
You have a body, like other men.
很好
Good.
那么睡吧
Then sleep.
好一点了吗？
Better?
好多了，你说的对
Much better. You were right.
休息吧，你学不乖吗？
Rest, rest. Can you not learn?
我已经学到教训了
Oh, I've learned all right.
我要走了，阿里
I'm going, Ali.
-为什么？ -为什么？
- Why? - Why?
天啊
Heavens.
为什么？
Why?
我想我已经完了
I've come to the end of myself, I suppose.
阿拉伯叛乱呢？
And the end of the Arab revolt?
我不是阿拉伯叛乱，阿里 我甚至不是阿拉伯人
I'm not the Arab revolt, Ali. I'm not even Arab.
你说人可以变成他想成为的人
A man can be whatever he wants. You said.
抱歉，我以为那是真的
I'm sorry. I thought it was true.
你证明了这一点
You proved it.
听着，阿里
Look, Ali. Look.
那是我，是什么颜色？ 那是我
That's me. What colour is it? That's me.
是我改不了的
And there's nothing I can do about it.
你说人可以变成他想成为的人
A man can do whatever he wants. You said.
他可以…
He can...
但他不能随心所欲
but he can't want what he wants.
这是决定他要什么的东西
This is the stuff that decides what he wants.
你也知道吧 我想什么都告诉他们
You may as well know. I would've told them anything.
我想告诉他们我是谁 我想告诉他们你要去哪里
I would've told them who I am. I would've told them where you were.
-我试着要说 -任何人都会那么做的
- I tried to. - So would any man.
我只是个平凡人
Well, any man is what I am.
我要回去跟艾伦比…
And I'm going back to Allenby to ask him for a job...
要一个平凡人的工作
that any man can do.
艾伦比在耶路撒冷
Allenby's in Jerusalem.
-我要做些轻松的事 -你？
- I'll make easy stages. - You?
对，我要做些轻松的事
Oh, yes. Easy stages.
听着，阿里，我想我可以有…
Look, Ali, I think I see a way of being just...
一种平凡的…
ordinarily...
快乐
happy.
我能拿走这个吗？
Can I take this?
它不干净喔
It is not clean.
对，但是很温暖
No, but it's warm.
他们呢…
And these...
带领他们到这里来 你不在乎他们吗？
having led them here, have you no care for them?
你带领他们，他们是你的了 相信你的人民
You lead them. They're yours. Trust your own people.
让我回到我的人民身边
And let me go back to mine.
-别忘了那些五人小组 -好吧
- I say, don't forget those form fives. - All right.
介意我加入吗？
Mind if I join you?
这是我的荣幸
Honoured, sir.
-回来了真好 -我们都听说你回来了，先生
- Good to be back. - We heard you were, sir.
-那边发生了什么事？ -哪里？
- What's doing out there? - Where?
-阿拉伯？ -是的，先生
- Arabia? - Well, yes, sir.
没什么，现在是淡季 这里呢？
Nothing much. Wrong time of year. What's doing here?
我们在安顿 我们盖了一座球场
We're settling in. We built a squash court.
太好了
Jolly good.
我得上去了
Well, I have to go up there.
那是借来的 有人把我的偷走了
It's borrowed. Someone pinched mine.
真是混蛋
Bloody wogs.
对啊，或许吧
Yes, probably.
球场那件事真是个好主意
Jolly good about the squash court.
他太夸张了，对吧？
Lays it on a bit thick, doesn't he?
早安
Morning.
-早安 -回来了真好
- Good morning. - Good to be back.
-我相信你，先生 -不，是真的
- I'll believe you, sir. - No, really it is.
嗨
Hello.
早安，直走进去
Morning. You're to go right in.
劳伦斯
Lawrence.
或我该叫你劳伦斯少校？
Or is it Major Lawrence?
长官
Sir.
将军，我要离开了
Well, general, I will leave you.
劳伦斯少校毫无疑问地要报告…
Major Lawrence doubtless has reports to make...
关于我的人民跟他们的弱点…
about my people and their weakness...
及让英国对他们 保持利益权的必要
and the need to keep them in the British interest.
法国人也有利益权 我们别忘了法国人
And the French interest too. We must not forget the French.
我说过了并没有这样的条约限制
I told you, no such treaty exists.
对，将军，你很勇敢地说谎 但说服力却不够
Yes, general, you have lied most bravely, but not convincingly.
我知道的确有条约存在
I know this treaty does exist.
条约？
Treaty, sir?
他的表演比你好，将军
He does it better than you, general.
当然他可以说是个阿拉伯人
But then, of course, he is almost an Arab.
你真的不知道吗？
You really don't know?
那么这到底是怎么一回事？
Then what the devil's this?
是我要求调离阿拉伯的申请信 先生
It's my request for release from Arabia, sir.
为什么？
Why? Are you sure you haven't heard of the Sykes-Picot Treaty?
你确定你没听说过 史凯奇皮哥特条约？
我没听过
No.
-我猜想得到 -别猜了，告诉他吧
- I can guess. - Don't guess. Tell him.
好了
Well, now...
史凯奇先生是一名英国公使
Mr. Sykes is as English civil servant.
皮哥特先生是一名法国公使
Monsieur Picot is a French civil servant.
史凯奇跟皮哥特见面 他们同意在战后…
Mr. Sykes and Monsieur Picot met, and they agreed that after the war...
英法该共享土耳其帝国
France and England should share the Turkish Empire.
包括阿拉伯在内
Including Arabia.
他们签订同意书而不是和约
They signed an agreement, not a treaty, sir.
同意书是有法律效力的
An agreement to that effect.
小偷之间或许还有尊严 但政客是无耻的
There may be honour among thieves, but there's none in politicians.
我们别生气
And let's have no displays of indignation.
你也许还不知道 但你有怀疑
You may not have known, but you certainly had suspicions.
如果我们是在说谎 你有一半也是在说谎
If we've told lies, you've told half-lies.
像我这样说谎的人 只是在隐瞒事实
And a man who tells lies, like me, merely hides the truth.
但说一半谎话的人 忘了事实是什么
But a man who tells half-lies has forgotten where he put it.
真相是我是个普通人
The truth is I'm an ordinary man.
你已经跟我说过了，戴丹
You might have told me that, Dryden.
我要一份普通的工作
And I want an ordinary job, sir.
那是我辞职的原因
That's my reason for resigning.
是因为私人的因素
It's personal.
-私人的因素？ -是的，长官
- Personal? - Yes, sir.
私人的因素？ 你可是一名公职军官
Personal? You're a serving officer in the field.
事实上你是一个 很重要的人物，你疯了吗？
And as it happens, a damned important one. Are you mad?
不，如果你不介意的话 我不想发疯
No, and if you don't mind, I'd rather not go mad.
那也是我的理由
That's my reason too.
听着，下个月十六号 我在大马士革有个大计划
Look, I'm making my big push on Damascus the 16th of next month...
你是其中的一部份
and you are part of it.
你明白吗？你是一个 大计划中重要的一部份！
Can you understand that? You're an important part of the big push!
我不要成为你的大计划中的一部份！
I don't want to be part of your big push!
那么你的阿拉伯朋友呢？
What about your Arab friends?
我没有阿拉伯朋友！ 我不要阿拉伯朋友！
I have no Arab friends! I don't want Arab friends!
你到底要什么？劳伦斯
What in hell do you want, Lawrence?
我说过了，我只想当个普通人
I've told you, I just want my ration of common humanity.
-劳伦斯 -什么？
- Lawrence. - Yes?
没什么，抱歉打断你们了
Nothing. Sorry I interrupted, sir.
没关系，谢谢你，戴丹先生
That's all right. Thank you, Mr. Dryden.
谢谢你
Thank you, sir.
我们为什么不…？
Why don't we...?
你背上有血
There's blood on your back.
-你要看医生吗？ -不必了
- Do you want a doctor? - No.
告诉我发生了什么事
Tell me what happened.
哎呀，那里发生了什么事？
Say, what goes on in there?
-没什么 -少来了！
- Nothing. - Oh, come on!
-真的没什么，什么事都没有 -他有麻烦了吗？
- No, really. Nothing at all. - Is the man in trouble?
应该如此，我们都有麻烦 生活充满了麻烦
I expect so. We all have troubles. Life's a vale of troubles.
他有麻烦就告诉我 我得保护他
Let me know if the man's in trouble. I've got a claim in that man.
-为什么？ -我让那孩子成了英雄
- What claim? - I've made that boy a hero.
当战争结束后 他想做什么都可以
When the war's over, he can be anything he wants.
是，现在他想当别人
Yes. Well, at the moment he wants to be somebody else.
麻烦借过一下，好吗？
Will you kindly allow me to pass?
逃避吧，戴丹
Walk away, Dryden, walk away.
总是在逃避，不是吗？
Always walking away, aren't you?
告诉你吧
Well, I'll tell you.
那里正在爆发脾气上的冲突
It's a clash of temperament that's going on in there.
不可避免地他们有一个半疯了
Inevitably, one of them's half-mad...
一个完全寡廉鲜耻
and the other, wholly unscrupulous.
我相信你的名字将会家喻户晓
I believe your name will be a household word...
而要知道谁是艾伦比 还要去战争博物馆查
when you'd have to go to the war museum to find who Allenby was.
你是我见过最不凡的人
You're the most extraordinary man I ever met.
别来烦我
Leave me alone.
-别来烦我 -真软弱的句子
- Leave me alone. - That's a feeble thing to say.
-我知道我不平凡 -我不是那个意思
- I know I'm not ordinary. - That's not what I'm saying.
好吧，我很不凡
All right, I'm extraordinary.
那又怎么样？
What of it?
不是很多人都注定好要成为伟人的 劳伦斯
Not many people have a destiny, Lawrence.
注定该成为伟大的人却感到害怕 那真的是太糟糕了
It's a terrible thing for a man to funk it if he has.
这是你的经验谈吗？
Are you speaking from experience?
不是
No.
那么是你的猜测
You're guessing, then.
我猜你错了
Suppose you're wrong.
你为什么会那么说？ 我们都知道我是对的
Why suppose that? We both know I'm right.
-对，我说对 -毕竟…
- Yes. I said, yes. - After all--
-十六号？ -你办得到吗？
The 16th?
我会给你很多钱
Can you do it? I'll give you a lot of money.
-大炮呢？ -我办不到
- Artillery? - I can't.
他们要的不是钱 他们当中的豪杰不是那么想的
They won't be coming for money, not the best of them.
他们要的是大马士革
They'll be coming for Damascus.
我会给他们大马士革
Which I'm going to give them.
那是我想要的
That's all I want.
你要我们夺走土耳其人的权利
All you want is someone holding down the Turkish Right.
但我会给他们大马士革的 我们会抢在你们之前赶到
But I'm going to give them Damascus. We'll get there before you do.
我们夺下它之后就要留下它
And when we've got it, we'll keep it.
叫那些政客现在烧了他们的合约
Tell the politicians to burn their paper now.
很公平
Fair enough.
公平？公平与此事何干？
Fair? What's fair got to do with it?
这是会发生的
It's going to happen.
我要很多钱
I shall want quite a lot of money.
所有的钱都是你的
All there is.
不要那么多
Not that much.
他们的当中的豪杰不是要钱的
The best of them won't come for money.
他们要的是我
They'll come for me.
别拍照！
No pictures!
不是要拍你，是要拍劳伦斯
It's not for you, it's for Lawrence.
他不介意拍照 他一点都不介意
He doesn't mind having his picture taken. He doesn't mind at all.
全世界只有一个劳伦斯
Well, there's only one Lawrence.
劳伦斯回来后 你跟他见过面吗？
Have you met Lawrence since he's come back?
见过
Yes.
-他变了，对吗？ -没有
- Changed, hasn't he? - No.
我说他变了 他变成一个不一样的人了
Oh, I'd say he had. Different man, I'd say.
那个土耳其将军在迪拉对他做了什么？
What did that Turkish general do to him in Deraa?
他在离开迪拉后还是一样 他只是谦卑了
He was the same man after Deraa. The same man, humbled.
英国人在耶路撒冷对他做了什么？
What did the English do to him in Jerusalem?
考倒我了，去问劳伦斯吧
Search me. Ask Lawrence.
-我问过了 -他怎么说？
- I did. - What did he say?
他大笑
He laughed.
他要我把哈利斯人叫来
He told me to gather the Harith here.
他还付我钱
He offered me money.
你拿了吗？
Did you take it?
没有，但很多人拿了
No. But many did.
-这是什么？ -这是我的保镖
- What is this? - This is my bodyguard.
这里每个人的人头都是有价格的
There is not a man without a price on his head.
-我的人头也有价格 -但他们是杀手
- There's a price on my head too. - But these are murderers.
酋长会吊死这些人的
The sheiks will hang these men.
他们是我的人
These men are mine.
劳伦斯，他们不了解阿拉伯叛乱
Lawrence, these things know nothing of the Arab revolt.
-你，艾拉波的盖坦 -长官？
- You, Ghitan of Aleppo. - Sherif?
-我们要往哪里去啊？ -大马士革，长官
- Where do we ride? - Damascus, sherif.
对，但为什么？
Aye, but for what?
沙利夫，为了劳伦斯
Sherif, for Lawrence.
-你买下了这些东西 -我买下这里一半的人，阿里
- You have bought these things. - I bought half the men here, Ali.
那不一样，他们不是普通人
That is different. These are not ordinary men.
我不要普通人，走吧！
I don't want ordinary men. Hut!
大马士革！
Damascus!
大马士革！…
Damascus! Damascus!
各位，骑兵队通过□兹瑞尔跟迪拉了
Very well, gentlemen. The cavalry's gone through Mazril and Deraa.
这真的是非常好，轮到你们了
Very good, by the way. Very good indeed. Now your turn.
如果敌人撤退 我们知道他们会撤退的…
If the enemy's retreating in any order, which we'll assume--
当然
Certainly.
他不会离麦拉德太远
He can't be far from Mallud...
所以我应该 在明天九点前能看到他
in which case I can have him within range by 0900 hours tomorrow.
太棒了，菲立普
Splendid. Philip.
这是现阶段最后的步兵支援部队
These are the last infantry supports going up now.
但星期三燧发枪团会到麦拉德
But Mallud, we could have the fusiliers there by Wednesday.
现在那样就够了，重要的是枪
That'll do for now. The guns are what matter.
有问题吗？
Any questions?
这只阿拉伯军队在右边 它是什么组成的？
This Arab army on the right, sir, what's it consist of?
非正式的骑兵队 大约有两千人
Irregular cavalry, sir. About 2000.
他们现在在哪里？
Where are they now?
-跟他们在一起的人才知道 -那么去找他们，我要知道
- Can only know by being with them. - Then get with them. I want to know.
痛击他们，查利
Pound them, Charley.
痛击他们
Pound them.
愿主保佑躺在那下面的人
God help the men who lie under that.
他们是土耳其人
They're Turks.
愿主保佑他们
God help them.
他简直是失去控制
Well, he's got the bit between his teeth all right.
他很傲慢吗？
Cocky?
不光只是傲慢而已
More than cocky, sir.
他简直是失去控制
He's got the bit between his teeth all right.
我告诉你 我想他会比我们早到大马士革
I tell you, sir, I think he'll get to Damascus before we do.
-除非… -除非？
- Unless... - Unless?
在□兹瑞尔外 有一队土耳其人挡在他前面
Well, there's a Turkish column in front of him, out of Mazril.
-□兹瑞尔有多少土耳其军队？ -有一旅
- What do the Turks have in Mazril? - A brigade, sir.
不知道他们现在在哪里
I wonder where they are now.
不准有囚犯
No prisoners.
大马士革，劳伦斯
Damascus, Lawrence.
劳伦斯，别这样
Lawrence, not this.
来吧，大马士革，劳伦斯
Go round. Damascus, Lawrence, Damascus.
通通杀光
No prisoners.
这以前是塔拉尔人的村落
This was Talaal's village.
塔拉尔人！
Talaal!
通通杀光！
No prisoners!
天啊
God.
天啊！
God!
够了，叫他们住手！
Enough. Enough! Make them stop!
少校！
Major!
劳伦斯少校！
Major Lawrence!
老天爷啊
Jesus wept.
那令你惊讶吗？班特利先生
Does it surprise you, Mr. Bentley?
你知道阿拉伯人是一只野蛮民族
Surely you know the Arabs are a barbarous people.
野蛮又残忍
Barbarous and cruel.
除了他们还会是谁？
Who but they?
你这个混蛋
Oh, you rotten man.
来吧，我帮你这个混蛋拍张照
Here, let me take your rotten bloody picture.
给那个该死的报纸
For the rotten bloody newspapers.
这是昨晚在大马士革割下来的 劳伦斯
These were cut last night, Lawrence, in Damascus.
大马士革！
Damascus!
把它们拿去给阿里长官
Take them to Sherif Ali.
告诉他
Tell him.
提醒他
Remind him.
-艾伦比在大马士革吗？ -他在附近
- Is Allenby in Damascus? - Near.
告诉阿里长官
Tell Sherif Ali that.
他们还没熟呢
They are not ripe.
(大马士革)
将军万岁！
General salute!
举枪！
Present arms!
枪放下！
Port arms!
劳伦斯在背后搞鬼，长官
Lawrence is behind it, sir.
全镇贴满了阿拉伯旗帜
The whole town is plastered with the Arab flag.
-那是什么时候的事？ -已经一天一夜，长官
- When? - A day and a night, sir.
他们来这里一天一夜了
They've been here a day and a night.
他们占据了这个小镇 他们做到了
They've occupied the town. They've done it.
他将总部设在镇公所
He's set up his own headquarters in the town hall.
除了镇公所外还占了什么？
What else beside the town hall?
电信局，邮局，发电厂…
Telephone exchange, post office, powerhouse...
医院，火车站 什么都占了，长官
hospitals, fire station. Everything, sir.
他们自称是阿拉伯国家议会
They call themselves the Arab National Council...
他们在镇公所里
and they're in the town hall.
他们是你的问题了，哈利
Well, they're your pigeon, Harry.
我们该怎么办？
What should we do?
尽快把他们弄出那里
Get them out of it, sir, quick time.
你觉得呢？戴丹
How about that, Dryden?
除非你想引起全面的抗争
Not unless you want a full-scale rising.
-那么要怎么做呢？ -费萨尔何时会到大马士革？
- What, then? - When will Feisal be in Damascus?
他搭专用的火车，两天内会到
By special train in two days' time.
两天
Two days.
最多两天，超过了 我无法再拖住他
Two days is what you asked for. I can't keep him out any longer.
-那不够吗？ -够了
- Isn't it enough? - Yes.
-我想够了 -我们不能什么都不做
- Ample, I should think. - We can't just do nothing.
为什么？通常那是最好的方法 拿点东西来给我们喝，崔西
Why not? It's usually best. Get us something to drink, Tracey.
崔西，没有进一步的命令 军队们都扎营不准离开
And Tracey, all troops to remain quartered until further orders.
技术单位也一样吗？
Does that apply to technical units?
特别是技术单位
Technical units particularly.
是的，长官
Yes, sir.
医药单位也一样吗？长官
Medicals too, sir?
恐怕是的，哈利
I'm af raid so, Harry.
医药单位也一样
Medicals too.
这里的人…
We here...
不是哈利斯人或哈威塔特人
are neither Harith nor Howeitat...
也不是其他部族的人
nor any other tribe, but Arabs...
我们是费萨尔王子 领导的阿拉伯议会的阿拉伯人
of the Arab Council, acting for Prince Feisal.
他侮辱我
He insulted me.
阿里长官说 电话现在属于哈威塔特人
Sherif Ali said that the telephones are in the care of the Howeitat...
它们现在都不通，这是真的
and they have ceased to work. And this is true.
电话不通是因为没电
They will not work because they are given no electricity.
电属于哈利斯人
The electricity is in the care of the Harith.
你一答话，就会血流成河
If you answer, there will be bloodshed.
你要跟我谈血流成河？
You speak to me of bloodshed?
我请求奥达阿布塔耶的原谅
I ask pardon of Auda Abu Tayi.
诚心的求吗？
Humbly?
诚心的求吗？哈利斯
Humbly, Harith?
是的，诚心的求
Yes, humbly.
这倒是新把戏
This is a new trick.
为什么没电？
Why is there no electricity?
我去过发电厂了，劳伦斯
I have been to that electrical house, Lawrence.
那里有三部大机器
There are three large machines.
他是说发电机！
He means generators!
所以呢？
So.
有一部在燃烧
One of them is burning.
所有机器都是这样
They are of an incredible size, but helpless.
It is so of all machines.
由它们烧吧，电话有什么作用？
Let them burn. What need of telephones?
-当然有用 -那么我们需要英国工程师
- The need is absolute. - Then we need English engineers.
不，把英国工程师带进来 英国政府也会跟着来
No. Take English engineers and you take English government.
带…
Take--
失火了
Fire has broken out.
-在哪里？ -金西比区
- Where? - The Jinsibi district.
-在那一区不重要 -火势会扩散的！
- It is not a district that matters. - It will spread!
那么叫消防队啊！
Then use the fire brigade!
我们试过了，但水不够强
We have tried, but there is no force in the water.
那你们得去提水
Then you must carry it.
-鲁阿拉人不提水的 -他们会做什么事？
- The Ruala do not carry water. - What else are they good for?
我们今天下午才接受陈情
We will hear petitions this afternoon.
今天下午！
This afternoon!
-战后我要面对这些事 -我们真的该想个办法啊
- I'll take this up after the war. - Surely we should do something, sir.
-这是老人的运动了 -你是老人吗？
- It's an old man's sport. - Are you an old man, sir?
我只能说责任真的很重大
All I can say is, sir, it's a heavy responsibility.
对不起
Sorry, sir.
或许是灯泡的问题
Maybe it's the bulb.
不是的
No, sir.
是电力的问题
It's the power.
他们要离开了
They're leaving.
那么就这样了
That's it, then.
他们这些乞丐长得不错，对吧？
Marvellous-Iooking beggars, aren't they?
算了吧，劳伦斯，跟我来
Leave it, Lawrence. Come with me.
-去哪里？ -回去
- Come where? - Back.
我了解你的心
I know your heart.
那是什么？
What is it?
是这个吗？
Is it this?
我说过了，这没什么
I tell you, this is nothing.
那是血吗？
Is it the blood?
在沙漠里流干的血 比你想像中还多
The desert has dried up more blood than you could think of.
我祈祷再也不必去沙漠
I pray that I may never see the desert again.
听我说，上帝
Hear me, God.
你会来的 沙漠是你唯一栖身之处
You will come. There is only the desert for you.
你呢？
What about you?
不，我要待在这里学习政治
No, I shall stay here and learn politics.
一种很低等的职业
A very low occupation.
我在遇见你时 根本没想过要这样
I had not thought of it when I met you.
你非常努力地 将大马士革交给我们
You have tried very hard to give us Damascus.
那是我来这里的原因
It's what I came for.
那么…
And then...
那是件伟大的事
it would be something.
对
Yes.
很伟大
Much.
-他是你的朋友吗？ -把你的手拿开
- He is your friend? - Take your hand away.
-你爱他 -我怕他
- You love him. - I fear him.
那你为什么哭？
Then why do you weep?
如果我怕他，也那么爱他…
If I fear him, who love him...
就知道他有多怕自己 多么的痛恨自己的了？
how must he fear himself, who hates himself?
把你的手拿开，哈威塔特人！
Take your hand away, Howeitat!
原来你还不是一个完全的政客
So you are not yet entirely politician.
还不是
Not yet.
现在有很多新把戏 而我是一只老狗了
Well, these are new tricks, and I am an old dog.
谢谢阿拉
And Allah be thanked.
我会告诉你…
I'll tell thee what...
当一个阿拉伯人 比你想像中还难，哈利斯
being an Arab will be thornier than you suppose, Harith.
我一生没看过这种事
In all my years, I've never seen anything like it.
这是阿拉伯议会的管辖范围？
It comes within the jurisdiction of the Arab Council.
在这种情况下 我想我该立刻接手
Under the circumstances, I think I must take over. Immediately.
毕竟在任何一种情况下 你都该服从命令
Under any circumstances at all, you must obey your orders.
不，长官，我不会的
No, sir, I will not.
控制一下你自己
Control yourself.
到镇公所那边 去看看他们说了什么
Now, go over to the town hall and see what they say.
市立医院那边已经尽力了
We did what we could in the civic hospitals.
但你忘了土耳其军事医院
But you forgot the Turkish Military Hospital.
那里有六百个床位 有约两千名的土耳其伤患
It has 600 beds. There are about 2000 Turkish wounded in it.
他们都是你宝贝的阿拉伯议会的责任
All of whom are the responsibility of your precious Arab Council.
情形是如何呢？
What's it like?
这太过份了！
This is outrageous!
太过份了！
Outrageous!
你这个王八蛋！
You filthy little wog!
“我的朋友劳伦斯” 如果我可以这么叫他的话
My friend Lawrence, if I may call him that.
“我的朋友劳伦斯”
" My friend Lawrence."
多少人会宣称 他们有权那么说呢？太光荣了
How many men will claim the right to use that phrase? How proudly.
他期盼着祖国的绿地
He longs for the greenness of his native land.
他渴望在苏利的葛德式房屋，对吧？
He pines for the Gothic cottages of Surrey, is it not?
他已经在想像他钓着鳟鱼
Already in imagination, he catches trout...
从事英国绅士的所有活动
and all the activities of the English gentleman.
你说的人是我 不是劳伦斯上校
That's me you're describing, sir, not Colonel Lawrence.
你升上上校了
You're promoted colonel.
是，为什么？
Yes. What for?
接受这荣誉吧，上校 表现出一点热忱来
Take the honour, colonel. Be a little kind.
身为上校，在船坞那边 你会有栋小木屋
As a colonel, you'll have a cabin to yourself on the boat home.
谢谢你
Then, thank you.
那么…
Well, then...
愿上帝保佑你
Godspeed.
这里不需要战士了
There's nothing further here for a warrior.
我们在讨价还价 那是老头子的工作
We drive bargains. Old men's work.
年青人制造战争 战争的本质…
Young men make wars, and the virtues of war are the virtues of young men.
就是年轻人的本质
未来的勇气跟希望
Courage and hope for the future.
老人则维持和平
Then old men make the peace.
和平的罪行是老人的罪行
And the vices of peace are the vices of old men.
不信任跟戒心
Mistrust and caution.
一定是这样的
It must be so.
我欠你的东西多到数不清
What I owe you is beyond evaluation.
发电厂，电信局，这些我都认输
The powerhouse, the telephone exchange, these I concede.
我得留住水厂
The pumping plant I must retain.
如果你留住了它 那么就无水可用了
If you retain it, there will be no water.
-我很希望你们能够帮忙 -那么你得扯下你的旗帜
- I shall be glad of assistance. - Then you must bring down your flag.
我不会的，若你手下要那么做 我的手下会反抗的
I shall not, and if your men attempt it, my men will resist it.
-你有手下吗？ -我的手下够打败你了
- Have you men? - Enough of that.
这件事可以造成了可怕的事件
It's a thing that makes an ugly incident.
我相信你的政府…
I'm sure your government...
不希望在和平会议上 以侵略者的身份出现
does not wish to appear at the peace conference as an aggressor.
喂！
I say!
是劳伦斯，对吧？
It's Lawrence, isn't it?
我能跟您握个手吗？
May I shake your hand, sir?
我只是想跟别人吹嘘一下而已
Just want to be able to say I'd done it, sir.
我们以前不认识吧？
Haven't we met before?
我想是不认识
Don't think so, sir.
对，不然我会记得的
No, no, sir, I should remember that.
大家都知道阿拉伯议会 是因我之名而得到权力
It is widely known the Arab Council took power in my name.
他们没有权力，那是错觉
They have no power. It's illusory.
错觉有时会很有力的
Illusions can be very powerf ul.
特别是…
Particularly...
当它们采取这样的模式
when they take this form.
全世界都很喜欢…
The world is delighted at the picture of Damascus...
被阿拉伯军队 解放大马士革的照片
liberated by the Arab army.
我得提醒你，那次行动 是由一位英国军官所领导
Led, may I remind you, by a British-serving officer.
对，劳伦斯 像是一把刀的两面利刃
Ah, yes. But then Lawrence is a sword with two edges.
我们都很高兴除掉他了，对吧？
We are equally glad to be rid of him, are we not?
我还以为我是个狠心人
I thought I was a hard man, sir.
你只是一个将军
You are merely a general.
我该当个国王的
I must be a king.
对不起
Excuse me, sir.
什么？
Well?
那个…
Well...
看来我们将会有一个 插上了阿拉伯旗帜的…
it seems we're to have a British waterworks...
英国水利局
with an Arab flag on it.
你觉得值得吗？
Do you think it was worth it?
那不关我的事 谢天谢地，我是个士兵
Not my business. Thank God I'm a soldier.
是的
Yes, sir.
你一直都是那么说
So you keep saying.
我猜…
You, I suspect...
你是这个大和解的主要推手
are chief architect of this compromise.
-你觉得呢？ -我吗？殿下
- What do you think? - Me, Your Highness?
总体来说 我后悔离开唐布利吉水井区
On the whole, I wish I'd stayed in Tunbridge Wells.
回家去吧
Well, sir. Going home.
Home, sir.
再见，多丽，我得离开你
Goodbye, Dolly, I must leave you
虽然离去会让我心伤
Though it breaks my heart to go